<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against sorrovv, in order to the obtaining of sanctified joy. An excellent treatise first written in French by N. Vedelius, then translated into Latine by Gallus Pareus, and now into English, by Cadwallader Winne, M.A.</title>
            <author>Vedel, Nicolaus, 1596-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1421_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868355</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 182:E1421[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against sorrovv, in order to the obtaining of sanctified joy. An excellent treatise first written in French by N. Vedelius, then translated into Latine by Gallus Pareus, and now into English, by Cadwallader Winne, M.A.</title>
                  <author>Vedel, Nicolaus, 1596-1642.</author>
                  <author>Winne, Cadwallader, b. 1622 or 3, translator.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[204] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Lathum [i.e. Latham], and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Bishops head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I¹²  K⁶.</note>
                  <note>With an initial blank leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan 11: 1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joy --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST SORROVV, IN Order to the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſanctified joy.</p>
            <p>An excellent treatiſe firſt written in French by <hi>N. Vedelius,</hi> then tranſlated into Latine by <hi>Gallus Pareus,</hi> and now into Engliſh,</p>
            <p>By <hi>Cadwallader Winne,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Lathum,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the Biſhops head in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:2"/>
            <head>The Authors Preface TO The moſt Noble and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Iames Micheley, Nicholas Vedelius</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth Grace &amp; Peace, through our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is no mortal man but is ſubject to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which ſo diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſweetneſſe of his life, if it hath any, that it turnes it altogether into bitterneſſe, and weariſomneſſe. It ſpares none, neither Kings, nor Princes, nor ſuch as are placed in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more eminent auhority;
<pb facs="tcp:120697:3"/> yea, the higher in dignity they bee, the more violently it ſets upon them; like waves, which daſh againſt the higheſt rocks in the ſea with moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement motion. The weapons which this moſt prevalent miſchiefe uſeth againſt us, are as manifold as the afflictions themſelves, whereunto we are expoſed in this life, wherein are all manner of moleſtations and miſeries, ſome more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous than others, not unlike to greater and leſſer living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that are found in the vaſt Ocean, and to divers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable creeping things on the earth; for one while one ſorroweth, as feeling ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall evill, and aſſaulted by
<pb facs="tcp:120697:3"/> ſome grievous and ſtinging temptation, which gives him moſt vehement blowes and ſhakes him, inſomuch, as it hurles him well-nigh into hell, that is deſperation; otherwhile ſome temporall miſeries aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault him, in regard whereof hee is of a heavy drooping countenance, his ſounder ſenſes diſordred, and his whole per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon depreſſed and caſt downe. And what Chriſtian is there, whom the miſerable and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous face of the Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts not? what houſe holder is there, that is not afflicted with the afflictions accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying marriage? Look how holier the ſtate is, and the more excellent be the bleſſings ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:4"/> the more grievous afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it ſuſtaines. It happens, that deſparity in nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and wife afflicts the mind, as when an <hi>Abigail</hi> is married to <hi>Baball,</hi> or a <hi>Moſes</hi> is conjoyned with <hi>Zephorah,</hi> that is ſo contrary to him. A bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren bed afflicts others, unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpoſition of children torment others, which at laſt brings them to a tragicall end: others lament the untimely death of their children, who for the preſent were their joy and comfort, and hopefull for the time to come; and their cutting off by ſome ſtrange and extraordinary miſchace heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens their griefe. Hither may be referred the death of one
<pb facs="tcp:120697:4"/> of the married perſons, and deceaſe of our beneficiall kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke and allies. Neither is the ſtate of ſingle life free, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, nay, innumerable mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations attend it, to wit, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſſe, crafty wiles of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, diſhoneſty, ignominy, contempt, poverty, loſſe of goods, impriſonment, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, imperfections both in body and ſoule, diſeaſes, and at laſt after the chaine of ſo many evils death it ſelfe, which either feare preconceived, or preſent invaſion preſents to his view. Moreover, neither doth that which is really cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous only breed in us ſorrow, but even joy it ſelfe carries with it this inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:5"/> as the body the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, either in reſpect thoſe things which thou wiſheſt fall not out ſo, as thou deſireſt they ſhould, or becauſe all manner of joy is as it were a certaine forerunner of ſorrow, wherein it ends. To ſay nothing here, that in that very time that proſperity on the one ſide cheers up thy ſpirit, ſome ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter thing on the other ſide is annexed, moving thee to be ſorrowfull; and as there is none that is not ſubject to this paſſion, ſo none can be found that is ſo bluntiſh, that wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth not to bee diſcharged therefrom. To which end di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers uſe divers meanes; for there be ſome that uſe meanes
<pb facs="tcp:120697:5"/> altogether unlawfull to be rid thereof, but are ſucceſſeleſſe; and more than that, are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times worſer than the diſeaſe; as <hi>Ahab</hi> did, following his wife <hi>Iezabells</hi> counſell, whom when ſhe ſaw ſo heavy that he would eat no bread, ſhee came unto him, and ſaid unto him, why is thy ſpirit ſo ſad, that thou eateſt no bread? let thy heart be merry, and I will give thee the vineyard of <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1 <hi>K.</hi> 21.5.7. for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> purpoſe ſhe ſubornes falſe witneſſe againſt the innocent, and with the wine and blood of <hi>Naboth</hi> makes the King merry and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; others think to withſtand this evil by other means, which are indeed in themſelves indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent;
<pb facs="tcp:120697:6"/> the uſe whereof is not able to drive it away, and the abuſe ignominious and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious unto him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth them, to wit, when ſtrong drink is given to him who is ready to periſh, and wine to thoſe that be of heavy hearts, that hee may drink and forget his poverty, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his miſerie no more, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.6,7. There are great many drinkers, an unhappy crue, who would ſuffocate and drown their ſorrowes in wine, which will at laſt bite like a ſerpent, and ſting like an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and cauſe thee to crie out, woe is me, woe is mee, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.29,32. Meat and muſick are of like nature, being abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:120697:6"/> and turned into carnall pleaſure, whereby many doe endeavour to put farre from them the day of calamity, as the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks, <hi>Am.</hi> 4.5,6,7. Hither may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred thoſe ſpeeches and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes which are framed by humane reaſon, to expell it, and to miniſter comfort to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, but they cannot doe him any good; for they leave him at laſt in perplexity of mind: diſcourſes I ſay, which are not onely able to drive away this evill, but are ſometimes frivolous, idle, fooliſh, yea, evill and pernicious. Such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation did <hi>Abſalon</hi> ſuggeſt ſometimes to his ſiſter <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> who fell into deſperation
<pb facs="tcp:120697:7"/> by reaſon of the violent inceſt wherewith <hi>Amon</hi> deflowred her. Hath <hi>Amon</hi> thy brother, ſaid hee, been with thee, but hold now thy peace, my ſiſter, hee is thy brother, regard not this thing, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.19. A fair ſpoken ſpeech, if credible, and good comfort forſooth, which was, that ſhe ſhould pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently beare with that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious and execrable infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, for that ſhe was deflowred not by any other but by her owne brother: But his words wrought nothing upon miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Thamar;</hi> for the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, that ſhe remained deſolate in her brother <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> houſe. Further, thoſe books which are forced, I know
<pb facs="tcp:120697:7"/> not with what fables; trifles; toies, or other narratives, whether true or feigned, are of the ſame bran, wherewith ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull men uſe to drive away the time and melancholy. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be referred the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of the body, as hunting, and the like lawful recreations, whereby the ſorrowfull man ſtrives to rid his mind of cares, wherein there is not only that defect found comon with other inſufficient meanes, in that when theſe recreations are fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed heavineſſe waxeth freſh againe; but there is alſo this diſcommodity therein, that they are not anſwerable to the nature of his diſeaſe, as being ill applied; theſe excerciſes
<pb facs="tcp:120697:8"/> working directly upon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but upon the mind indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and accidentally onely; now ſorrow is inherent in the mind, and not in the body, the plaſter therefore is to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the part ill affected, and where the enemy lurkes, there hee is to bee ſought for. Hee that doth otherwiſe, goes about with deſperate <hi>Abſalons</hi> ſervants, who purſuing <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> inſtead of ſearching for them in the place where they had hid themſelves, gave credence to the lying ſpeech of a certaine woman, and returned, not finding them, to the place whence they came at firſt. But ſith ſorrow lieth hid in the mind, it is neceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:120697:8"/> with <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to enter into the cave where the enemy lies hid, to draw him out thence to trample upon him, and cut him off preſently. Thus much of thoſe which uſe theſe indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent meanes. There are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which imploy themſelves in the laudable buſineſſe of this life, even thoſe which each mans vocation exacteth of him, that thereby they may diſpoſſeſſe themſelves thereof, and troubleſome cogitations; which though they ſeem more available, and are more becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming than thoſe which we have before touched, yet though ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and honeſt in themſelves, are not of any validity to drive away this evil now in queſtion.
<pb facs="tcp:120697:9"/> All the benefit that one can procure thereby, is, that for a time they make him forget his miſery, but they can in no wiſe conferre upon him ſuch goodneſſe as will rejoyce him. The beſt and moſt ſoveraigne remedy then is that, which will not onely chaſe away the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the preſent evil, but will exhibit that goodneſſe that will produce gladneſſe as ſoone as conceived in the mind, whence before it was either through ignorance or forgetfulneſſe expelled and baniſhed. In a word, the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull man recovers of his diſeaſe, when the peccant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is driven out by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary gladneſſe of mind, which
<pb facs="tcp:120697:9"/> as it is ſought for by few, by reaſon of mens naturall blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo it is very requiſite to every one that wiſheth well to himſelfe; whoſoever will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie this remedy ſhall by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience find that other remedies in reſpect therof, are but as the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks, ſongs to a heavy heart, and as vinegar up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Nitre, which remedy wee ſhall handle in this treatiſe, by Gods aſſiſtance, and as farre as our weakneſſe will give us leave, performe that office gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> by the Holy Ghoſt; we exhort, comfort the feeble minded, 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 5.14. And here firſt of all, I proteſt, that while I exhort the faithful man to chaſe it away, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:120697:10"/> the grounds or reaſons hereof, my intent is not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him of all ſenſe of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and that hee ſhould not be ſorrowfull at any time; this were to lay aſide all humanity and chriſtianity, there being a kind of ſorrow, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and becomes every man: but my purpoſe is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him as farre as I am able, ſo as he may beware as much as in him lieth beforehand of the aſſaults of it, or if it ſets upon him, not to ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be foiled, and vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, neither ſo to poſſeſſe him, as it doth the perverſe and wicked man, concerning whom <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaks; trouble and anguiſh ſhall make him afraid;
<pb facs="tcp:120697:10"/> they ſhall prevaile againſt him as a King ready to battell, <hi>Iob</hi> 15.24. In ſhort, my purpoſe is to afford him meanes, if hee be affected therewith as he is a man, wherewith hee may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due it as a Chriſtian, and bee ſenſible that as he is not a man that never feeles the brunt of it, ſo hee is not a Chriſtian, which will not couragiouſly drive it away when it ſets upon him; the ſpirit of man, ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, will ſuſtaine his infirmity, but a wounded ſpirit who can beare, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. And in another place, if thou faint in the day of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity thy ſtrength is ſmall, <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.10. By which words the ſpirit of God declares, that
<pb facs="tcp:120697:11"/> that man is quite undone that is familiar therewith. It ſtands therefore upon the children of God in afflictions to be vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly ſpirited, and heroicall, that not yeelding thereto, they may become victorious and triumph cheerfully, being la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with rich ſpoiles; this is our drift. Secondly, I proteſt my ſcope is not to drive the faithfull man to all manner of joyes, not ſuch joyes where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with the wicked are poſſeſſed, who rejoyce to doe evill, and delight in the frowardneſſe of the wicked, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.14. nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther levels my diſcourſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wordly mirth, grounded upon heaps of riches, pleaſures, commodities, and honours o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:11"/> this world: Gods children ſhould herein ſo behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to obſerve continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that they rejoyce as though they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.30. That therefore ſhould not be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for reall mirth, which is attributed to fooles. The heart of fooles, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> is in the houſe of mirth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.4. and is nothing elſe, but the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſuch as have not their right wits about them, which is alſo altogether unprofitable, as he ſaith in another place; I ſaid in my heart go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, and therefore enjoy pleaſure, and behold this is alſo vanity: I have ſaid of laughter, it is mad, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:12"/> of mirth what doth it. And in another place hee ſaith, it is momentany, and ſoone peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth; for as the crackling of thornes under a pot, ſo is the laughter of a foole; this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vanity. Adde hereunto that ſorrow attends that mirth, or followeth it cloſe at the heeles; even in laughter the heart is ſorrowfull and the end of that mirth is heavineſſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.13. for theſe cauſes the Holy Ghoſt preferreth by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſorrow before this kind of mirth. It is better to go to the houſe of mourning, than the houſe of feaſting, for that is the end of all men, and the living will lay it to heart; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is better than laughter; for
<pb facs="tcp:120697:12"/> by the ſadneſſe of the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the heart is made better, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.2,3. wee exhibit not here then this kind of mirth, but ſanctified joy, whereunto Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth us, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord alwayes, and againe I ſay rejoyce, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. that joy, I ſay, that is grounded upon Gods grace and benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence towards us, and is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and teſtimony of ouradop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that joy w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is a concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of Gods children, &amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they are moſt of al ſmitten with the ſtroaks of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and gives us a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter luſtre in the houre of death, which is ſo terrible to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of this world; that joy which is begun in this world,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:13"/> and perfected in that which is to come, and endureth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for your joy, ſaith our Saviour Chriſt, no man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth from you, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.22. That joy, I ſay, whereby wee ſayle with a proſperous gale the ſea of this life, poſſeſſing tranquility of mind in the midſt of the moſt grievous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities wherewith it is toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, enjoying theſe temporall goods, which God hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon us; as alſo joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully finiſhing the courſe of our life and ſpirituall calling, being not unmindfull of that ſpeech of <hi>Solomon;</hi> There is no good among men, but for every man to rejoyce, and to doe good in his life; as alſo, that
<pb facs="tcp:120697:13"/> every man ſhould eat &amp; drink, and enjoy the good of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; it is the gift of God, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.12,13. Thirdly, I have not laboured herein for them that live without the fear of God, perſiſting in their ungodlineſſe and heart-hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; In ſo doing, I ſhould but write upon the ſand; yea, I ſhould bee ſet naught by them, as the Holy Ghoſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, he that reproveth a ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner getteth to himſelf ſhame, hee that rebuketh a wicked man getteth to himſelfe a blot, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.7. wherefore wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort them in no wiſe, but ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon we them with St. <hi>Iames,</hi> to be afflicted, to mourne and weep, and to turne their laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:120697:14"/> to mourning, and their joy to heavineſſe, <hi>Ia.</hi> 4.9. But we labour herein for thoſe ſoules that are deſolate, and overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſorrow, for oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſciences; in a word, for the children of God, that are in afflictions, and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Fourthly, it is manifeſt, I give way to Godly ſorrow, which worketh repentance not to be repented of, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. for ſith my intent in this ſmall treatiſe is to edifie Gods children, it is evident that wee allow them that ſorrow which is linked with repentance, and hath no other originall than it, and cannot be in any progreſſe without it; but being poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:120697:14"/> therewith, wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware from falling into deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and attributing that efficacy thereunto, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs onely to Gods mercy. But hereof, by Gods aſſiſtance, in another place, that wee may handle all things decently, and in order, wee will propoſe the grounds or reaſons, which ſhould move the faithfull to bid adieu to ſorrow, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily to rejoyce. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are of two ſorts, whereof ſome are drawne from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof, which we exhibit in two tables, that every man perceiving the nature of his diſeaſe may look for a remedy, and ſo bruiſe the ſcorpion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his wound, that ſo hee may
<pb facs="tcp:120697:15"/> be healed and recovered. The firſt table preſents us with the deformity of this Monſter; The ſecond with the hurtfull effects thereof. In the ſecond ſort, of the grounds of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied mirth, the ſpirituall goods which God communicates with the faithfull, ſhall be in the firſt place declared. In the ſecond place, the temporall goods which the faithfull for the preſent enjoyes by Gods grace and goodneſſe ſhall bee treated of. In the third place, wee will ſpeak of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and thoſe temporall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which the faithfull ſhould expect to receive for the future at his liberality. In the fourth place wee will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:15"/> that not onely the benefits, but even the miſeries of this life yeeld matter of joy. Laſtly, wee teach that the godly man, in reſpect of his condition, as being a traveller in this world, ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſorrow, and go on cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly. Behold, moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sir, the matter, end, and order, of this treatiſe which I preſent unto your Honour, in regard I think my ſelfe enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to offer unto you privat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a token, and to erect pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely a monument of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient friendſhip; which as it hath ſprouted about thirteene yeares ſince, ſo it grew toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in good ſtudies and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the nouriſhment and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:16"/> knot of our converſation. Your honour, I perſwade my ſelfe, hath experience of the vertue and efficacy of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies which this little trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe holds forth: for if there be any living that can uſe, and apply them when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, Your Honour abounds therewith, for you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at Gods hands many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent benefits, aſwell temporall as ſpirituall; the enjoyment whereof ſhould provoke you to rejoyce in God, and arme your ſelfe againſt temptations, for which every faithfull man ſhould prepare himſelfe; for God hath, not without cauſe, conferred upon you ſo many benefits, ſince for the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:120697:16"/> part the bountiful grace which God powrs upon his children, is as it were an harbinger of the ſubſequent aſſaults which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in this life. The great Emperour and Commander, under whoſe banner all the faithfull warre and fight, armes not his ſoldiers with weapons, to the end they may lie dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant before their enemies ſight; which weapons are thoſe benefits, which flow from his grace in Chriſt Jeſus, which he preſents us with in his word, inſtructing us thereby how to wraſtle with all adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and giving us means to be made more than conquerours in all temptations. Bleſſed is the man that can turne the
<pb facs="tcp:120697:17"/> ſignes of Gods grace into wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, the badges of peace into warlike inſtruments, the plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhares into ſwords, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hooks into ſpeares, <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.10. ſo that hee may ſay, when need requires, I am ſtrong. Sir, you haue a Magazine of theſe weapons, and can with dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty handle them, and know withall how to manage them skilfully, againſt heavineſſe, and ſorrow, wherein you are involved, by reaſon of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature death of <hi>Mark Michely</hi> your brothers ſonne, ſome three dayes ſince. Now if this treatiſe can mitigate your griefe, and in due time aboliſh it, I ſhall as heartily rejoyce, as I do now condole and grieve;
<pb facs="tcp:120697:17"/> and alwayes honour his emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent vertue and piety, whereof hee gave proofe in this City. I doubt not but you will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the remedies which I doe here propoſe, the efficacy whereof I would have you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute unto me, who am no body but unto Gods word, whence I have drawne the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients of this Antidote. I wiſh that you, moſt Noble Sir, and all your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (which had rather forſake the pleaſures of <hi>Italy,</hi> and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of that ſpirituall <hi>Egypt,</hi> than eſcape the reproach of the croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch ſplendor of zeale, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and piety derived from the patents to the off ſpring,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:18"/> doth as yet ſhine in the eyes of all men, may reap moſt joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fruit of divine reverence, which dwelleth in your hearts aſwell in this life, as in that which is to come. This I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh from <hi>Geneva,</hi> 1630.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. VEDELIVS</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:18"/>
            <head>To his honoured Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>William Winne,</hi> of <hi>Glinne,</hi> in the County of <hi>Merio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,</hi> Eſq.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving tranſlated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my ſlender faculty, at <hi>the requeſt</hi> of a worthy learned friend of mine, whom I ſhall not here particularize, as deſerving mention by a Diviner pen, out of Latin into Engliſh this enſuing treatiſe, being
<pb facs="tcp:120697:19"/> written Originally in French by <hi>N. Vedelius</hi> Doctor and Profeſſor of Divinity, I reſolved with my ſelfe to expoſe it to the cenſorious view of the world, prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your name thereunto, though I am not ignorant, that what I doe herein em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blazons my imperfections and weakneſſe, which I had rather do in this nature for this time than ſet forth ſome abortive, weak, feeble iſſue of my own brain. And though the faſhion and habit of this Infant, in this new dreſſe, be
<pb facs="tcp:120697:19"/> plain and homely, ſutable to the place wherein it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived; yet I perſwade my ſelfe, for I have ſo much rhetorick, you will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe it a gracious and mild aſpect. I paſse not though ſuch will frowne, and look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquint upon it, as think no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy peruſall, but what bluſters in high lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Vertue, aſſure your ſelfe, may lie hid under ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet frize, aſwell as a ſcarlet cloake. The attire denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates not a complete Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, no more than the beard
<pb facs="tcp:120697:20"/> the Phyloſopher; give it then entertainment, and hug it with your beſt affections, aſwell in reſpect it may prove, in this mournfull age, a Cordiall and reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, for your declining age, as becauſe it ſpeaks not the language of the ſcurrilous, malevolent, abuſive brats of the ſwelling fancies of theſe laſt times, wherein mens minds labour with ſtrange and fearfull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations: times, I ſay, which have produced, as <hi>Africa,</hi> ſome uncouth miſhapen mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;
<pb facs="tcp:120697:20"/> I had almoſt ſaid, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning bitter inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, I meane, which are no better than Libels, which are ſtiled, and not without cauſe, by a moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, learned, eloquent perſonage of this land,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Fran. Bacon.</hi>
               </note> Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males of ſedition, ſuch as were never ſeene in this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate region. Zeale miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governed hath quickned them into a numerous ſwarme, like ſo many Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Locusts, and are compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led perchance by the Adorers of that ſpirituall Egypt and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:21"/> Sodom, embracers of that woman ſpoken of in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, which is drunken with the bloud of the Saints, and with the bloud of the Martyrs of Ieſus, <hi>Rev. 17.6.</hi> inſomuch, that they have fluttered, and taken their flight into every corner of this Kingdome, darkning even to conſternation and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the cleare aire of truth. The Preſse hath groan'd is bringing to light ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal il-boding ſpurious brats, who aſsoon as they are borne, to uſe the Pſalmiſts words,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:21"/> go aſtray &amp; ſpeak lies wipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood, which have made it their only deſign, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and work, to burſt aſunder the bowels of our mother the Church, and tear in pieces the ſeamleſse coat of Chriſt. But Sir, for this poore Infant I preſent unto you, it ſpeaks not daggers, it deſpiſeth not dominions, nor ſpeaks evill of dignities; it railes not at principalities and powers; It comes not with a rod, but with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of meekneſse; It exhorts lovingly the ſorrowfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb facs="tcp:120697:22"/> man to take courage, and rejoyce in the Lord; It ſheweth ſorrow to bee good for nothing but ſinne; It ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth the faithfull man to be of the Syrens diſpoſition, whom they report to be moſt joyfull, when moſt of all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and compaſſed about with ſtormes and tempest. It teaches him to be of that Godly mans temper, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by one of the Ancients, who though he had loſt all his goods and ſubſtance, was ſo farre from being ſorrowfull, that this was his prayer,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:22"/> Lord, thou knoweſt where all my goods are laid up in ſtore, he meant in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, where neither moth doth corrupt, and where theeves doe not break through and steale, <hi>Matt. 6.19.</hi> a Kingdome incorruptible, undefiled, that fadeth not away, <hi>1 Pet. 1.4.</hi> a Kingdome, where there is an induring ſubſtance, <hi>Heb. 10.34.</hi> Where God ſhall wipe away all tears from our eyes, where ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying, nor pain, <hi>Rev, 21.4.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:23"/> but ſpirituall joy ſurpaſsing mans understanding, and that for ever, wherewith the God of all comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation crowne your hoary haires after fulneſſe of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſse, and dayes in this world, which ſhall bee ſome part of the prayers, early and late, of your moſt obſervant, obedient, and dutifull ſonne,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Cadwallader Winne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:23"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Chapters following.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. The firſt ground or reaſon why the faithfull man ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce worldly ſorrow is drawn from its filthineſſe and deformity.</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. The ſecond ground or reaſon is drawn from the pernicious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof.</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. The third ground or reaſon why the faithfull man ſhould aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it, and be joyfull, is drawn from Gods ſpirituall grace in Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:24"/>
               <item>CHAP. IV. The fourth ground or reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the corporall benefits conferred by God.</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. The fift ground or reaſon is drawn from Gods providence, and that the faithfull man ſhould for the future hope to receive corporall benefits.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. The ſixth ground or reaſon is, that afflictions themſelves yield matter of joy.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. The ſeventh and laſt ground or reaſon is drawne from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the faithfull man in this world, which conſiſteth herein, that hee is a traveller journeying into his countrey.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:24"/>
            <head>AN Antidote againſt ſorrow.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The firſt ground or reaſon why the faithfull man ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce worldly ſorrow is drawn from its filthineſſe and deformity.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orldly ſorrow where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou art now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed winds it ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy heart, under the ſpecious colour of lawfull care, under the pretence of decorum or comelineſſe, naturall honeſty, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:25"/> of pittying thee, as alſo under the vizard of doing thee good and friendſhip, and of procuring thee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment. But I would have thee know, that there lies in it nothing but trecherie and deceit, which thou ſhalt moſt manifeſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the vizard thereof being pull'd off, by viſibly diſcerning the face of this chymera: for then thou ſhalt find it a monſter excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding deformed, impure, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, moſt cruell, furious, and pernicious.</p>
               <p>In this Chapter it ſhall ſuffice us to unfold in ſome proportionits de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and more fully in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Wee affirme therefore ſorrow being predominant in mans heart to be a filthie paſſion, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together infamous, as burdening him with reproach and ignominy, which will more cleerly appeare conſidering it in relation to God, his Neighbour, and laſtly him in
<pb facs="tcp:120697:25"/> whom it freely domineeres. In relation to God it is manifeſt, that it is contrary unto him divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes; for it ſets light by, and contemnes his commandment, often enjoyning us heartily to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I ſay rejoyce,</hi> Phil. 4.4. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant hereunto is the counſell of the wiſe man, <hi>Give not over thy mind to heavineſſe, and afflict not thy ſelfe in thine own counſell, love thy own ſoule and comfort thy heart, and remove ſorrow farre from thee,</hi> Eccleſ. 30.21,24. And againe, <hi>take not heavineſſe at heart, drive it away and remember thy laſt end,</hi> Eccleſ. 38.20. Neither doth it leſſe thwart Gods providence, for it cauſeth one to thinke that the hand of God hath not wrought his afflictions; neither faſtneth hee his eyes upon divine providence, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in words acknowledging it: But if hee would firmly believe
<pb facs="tcp:120697:26"/> afflictions to be the worke of his providence, he ſhould find therein more matter of joy than ſorrow, the afflictions of the godly being badges of Gods love, tending to the good and ſalvation of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ones. And though he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to think upon God, and to acknowledge his viſitation upon him with this or that affliction, hee preſently offends him another manner of way; for he is impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and by his frequent murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſeth God himſelfe. That diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth him which is acceptable to God, and complaines of his wil, ſaying, <hi>Thou art a bloudy husband to me,</hi> Exod. 4.26. And with that wicked ſervant, <hi>I knew thou wert a hard man,</hi> Mat. 25.24. and hating that which is a token of Gods love, and being in extreme danger of the loſſe of his ſpirituall life, hee ſpills that medicine which ſhould have been ſo neceſſary for him, yea,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:26"/> blames the Phyſician himſelfe for ſtretching a healing helping hand: It cauſes him to be pagan like, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull of Gods goodneſſe, and the verity of his promiſe. It robs God of his fatherly care he hath of us infringing that hope which ſhould be repoſed in him: Hence the Apoſtle joynes it with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſaying, <hi>That yee ſorrow not as others which have no hope,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4,13. It makes him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull blotting out his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance ſo many corporal and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſſings whereof hee hath had experience by Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which if hee would thinke upon, he would not ſuffer himſelfe to bee carried headlong thereby. And becauſe his mind is fixed upon evill, his affliction alſo being either real or imaginary, he makes little or no reckoning of Gods benefits, but buries them in oblivion, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an execrable brand of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.
<pb facs="tcp:120697:27"/> It makes him not to imploy all the faculties both of his body and ſoule in Gods ſervice with ſuch a meaſure of zeale as is meete; <hi>Serve the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Prophet David, <hi>with gladneſſe, and come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his preſence with a ſong,</hi> Pſal. 100.2. Thou ſhalt rejoyce in thy feaſt &amp;c. <hi>Seven dayes ſhalt thou keep a ſolemne feaſt unto thy Lord thy God, and therefore ſhalt thou ſurely rejoyce,</hi> Deut. 16.14,15. This alacrity in ſerving God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not even in the leaſt degree be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by him; nay hee is as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in all the actions of his life, as he is negligent in Gods ſervice. And thus thou ſeeſt how hainouſly he offends God. In relation to his neighbour, hee is ſuſpicious, unaffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, unmannerly, teſty, contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, whereby hee renders himſelfe vitiouſly deformed, hatefull, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious. In relation to himſelfe, it makes him to incurre no leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb facs="tcp:120697:27"/> and ignominy than filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for generally it argues the weakneſſe of his underſtanding, joyned with fooliſhneſſe, yea, beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and declares him to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelfe, whereby it happens that hee judgeth fooliſhly of the cauſe of his ſorrow, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth falſehood inſtead of truth: Hence the Apoſtle joynes it with falſe opinion, ſaying, <hi>No ſorrow for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous,</hi> Heb. 12.11. where wrong judgement is taxed which accompanieth it, particularly it makes him ignorant of his owne condition, and to take, at leaſt for a time, no conſideration of himſelfe: for being call'd hereunto, to wit, to be a joyfull heire of the Kingdome of Heaven by the right of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, coheire with Jeſus Chriſt, and Lord of all the Creatures, he ought not to make his firme aboad in this world, neither to place his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:120697:28"/> therein, but as a ſojourner to travell to his heavenly Countrey. Wherefore he ſhould alwayes go forward, not ſtand ſtill, much leſſe retreat backe, but deſpiſing the world, and all the concupiſcences thereof, couragiouſly to remove all obſtacles hindring him thither, and to place his happineſſe in God, of whoſe love whoſoever is once perſwaded, doubts not but hee will lead him by his fatherly providence in this deſart and pilgrimage. Wherefore he ſhould carry with him a high, generous, and undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpirit, which is altogether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming the ſonnes of the King of Kings. This he ſhould have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before his eyes, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and ſeriouſly conſider there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; how wiſely then would hee order his life and converſation? with what happineſſe would hee live in this world? But ſorrow as a deadly phrenſy buries all theſe
<pb facs="tcp:120697:28"/> things in oblivion, ſo that it makes one forget his originall, and eſtate, his owne name, nay, himſelfe; It makes him wholy bent upon this world, miſerably torturing himſelfe for the loſſe which hee either ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaines, or feares to be, of honours, riches, pleaſures, or the like, as may be ſeene in that young man, who when he had heard he ſhould ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine the loſſe of his riches, went away ſorrowfull, leaving Jeſus, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.22. which diſcovered him to be deſperately enamoured of this world, and to ſeek his abode and ſolace therein, whereas hee ſhould ſeek for tranquillity in Heaven, and felicitie in God. It comes to paſſe that he is penſive upon any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſordering, afflicting, mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, and ſuffering himſelfe to be eaſily miſſed out of the way to his heavenly countrey. In a word, he is like a fooliſh traveller, who being given over to commit innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable
<pb facs="tcp:120697:29"/> fooleries can never attain to his journeyes end. And there is another ſort of fooliſhneſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable in him; for after he hath once wandred out of the King of heavens high-way, hee ſo miſgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns himſelfe, as that without any circumſpection he takes hold of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, which even at the firſt bluſh offers it ſelfe to his view. He is not contented to bee exerciſed with more waighty occaſions, and afflictions; but as if his life were not miſerable enough of it ſelfe, he fabricates to himſelfe daily new miſeries, ſo that he will be ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full upon any ridiculous, vile, and ſlight matter, whereof if hee bee queſtioned by a certain <hi>Jonadab</hi> a faithfull friend, <hi>Thou being the Kings ſonne, why art thou leane from day to day,</hi> 2 Sam. 13.4. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he will not be leſſe aſhamed to confeſſe the cauſe of his ſorrow, than <hi>Amon</hi> was of the intended
<pb facs="tcp:120697:29"/> deteſtable inceſt. Hee is vexed at one ſmall word, though well ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet taken by him in ill part; or if one ſpeak amiſſe, hee will inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it to be worſer: He will be ſo farre moved by an oblique aſpect, by a vaine and counterfeit Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, by a ſlight fault of his Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant, and man-ſervant, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all the benefits he poſſeſſeth in heaven and earth, which is a thing unbefitting him, who is the ſonne of the King of Kings, and heire of the Kingdome of heaven. Beſides, ſorrow diſcovers in him another kind of fooliſhneſſe, in that hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth thereby the ſoule in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the body, which ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the body, and it onely be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a diviner ſpirit: And were<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as hee ſhould rather oftentimes ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, ſet light by, and in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure concoct it, he out of a kind of brutiſh ſelfe-love had rather be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable than happy, of a crazed than
<pb facs="tcp:120697:30"/> found mind. Moreover, it ſhewes him to be abject, and deſtitute of a generous and heroicall ſpirit, which reſides in the hearts of the children of God; neither endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours he with ſuch a courage as is fit to remove the obſtacles, which in this life hinder him from the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but ſtoopeth to the difficulties that withſtand him; he is of a vile abject ſpirit, and as much as in him lyeth, renounceth his owne right thereunto. Further, the deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof ſhewes it ſelfe by exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſymptomes; It makes him to be of a heavy countenance, poring upon the earth, oftentimes to weep, not unlike a ſilly foole or ſoft wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; otherwhile his ſpeech failes him, or his tongue faultereth; yea, by his ſilence he ſpeaks his infamy. He abandons the ſocietie of men, hiding himſelfe in corners, even as the malefactor to eſcape the ſight
<pb facs="tcp:120697:30"/> of the magiſtrate. It impaires his good name or reputation, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the cauſe inducing him thereunto is unknowne, or of no reckoning; thereupon he renders himſelfe ſuſpicious that hee hath committed, or is about to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate ſome heynous ſinne, but this ſuſpicion is oftentimes falſe, as may appeare by <hi>Ely</hi> the Prieſt, who thought <hi>Anna Elkanahs</hi> wife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in bitterneſſe of ſoule to bee drunke, grounding his conjecture upon ſome ſignes he had obſerved in her, miſperſwading himſelfe. This conjecture notwithſtanding is ſometimes true, whereof <hi>Amon</hi> is an example, who when hee had an intention to commit inceſt with his ſiſter, was vexed, inſomuch that he fell ſick by reaſon of anguiſh of heart. How <hi>Ahab</hi> was overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſorrow, when hee could not enjoy another mans goods, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> vineyard! How heavy was
<pb facs="tcp:120697:31"/> 
                  <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Tyrant, when his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious will could not put into execution the devaſtation of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem?</hi> And was not <hi>Herod</hi> ſorry, becauſe of the raſh oath hee made to that infamous <hi>Herodias</hi> which beheaded <hi>John Baptiſt?</hi> It is a ſymptome oftentimes of hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which our Saviour intimates, when he ſaith, <hi>Be not as the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites with a ſad countenance,</hi> Mat. 9.16. Further, experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that thoſe that are more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally prone thereunto are proud, and cruell. What hath been ſaid doth manifeſt its deformity, and ſhew that it out-ſtrips in filthineſſe and uglineſſe even thoſe cruell beaſts which ſuperſtitions <hi>Aegypt</hi> did adore; and now ſeeing thou art one of the number of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, beware thou giveſt it an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in thy ſoule, the temple of the Holy Ghoſt, but rather let thy mind abound in all godly mirth,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:31"/> which is as befitting thy eminent condition, as ſorrow is unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He that rejoyceth according to Gods commandment receives adverſity at his hands, as thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as proſperity; He patiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits his neck to the yoake; Hee knowes the croſſe to be the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of Gods love, and a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne cure for his ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, the end of his conflict victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the crowne of the lambe, and eternall glory; He confides in God, and reſteth upon his promiſes, committing his care unto him to provide all neceſſaries; Hee payes his vowes, he offers daily the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of proſperity, and with the calves of his lips his morning and evening oblation; he ſerves God cheerfully, and with fervent zeale; he is at peace with his neighbour, and meekly covers his failings; he knowes this world to be a place of pilgrimage, heaven to bee his
<pb facs="tcp:120697:32"/> countrey whither hee ſteeres with cheerfulneſſe, not ſuffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be miſled out of the way thither by any occaſion, though ſeeming weighty to fleſh and bloud. He placeth his happineſſe in God; he makes a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſuch grievous afflictions as come of their owne accord, and thoſe whereinto hee plunges him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himſelfe: The former as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable he patiently endures, the latter hee warily eſchews. Hee knows that his ſoule is not a ſlave or vaſſall to his body, but Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. He reſiſteth adverſitie with an unconquerable courage; he is of ſuch an heroicall mind as beſeemes him who is the Prince of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; his countenance void of hypocriſie and pride ſpeaks the happineſſe and majeſtie appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated onely to Gods children, yea, his countenance and all his geſtures intimate his mirth and integrity,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:32"/> which reſteth in his boſome, and evidently ſhew he is in no wiſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this world. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his body being his viler and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobler part is here upon earth, yet his ſoule being the nobler and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath its converſation in heaven; like <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, whoſe lower part was ſet upon the earth, the top reaching to heaven. He obeyes the advice of the wiſe man, who ſaith, <hi>A cheerfull and good heart will have care of his meat and diet,</hi> Eccl. 30.27. that is, will rid it ſelfe of impieties and ſorrow, which as they are exceeding unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming, ſo they are, as hereafter ſhall bee declared, pernicious and hurtfull. Here thou ſeeſt a briefe character of ſuch a one as rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the Lord; judge then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou doſt not amiſſe in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring vice before vertue, filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before honeſty, monſtrous deformity before heavenly beauty,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:33"/> the repreſentation or Idaea of hell, where there is nothing but weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of teeth, before the reſembance of God and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly felicity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. The ſecond ground or reaſon is drawne from the pernicious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof.</head>
               <p>HItherto thou haſt ſeen one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly table, now thou ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold another more deformed than the former; for the vitioſity of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row conſiſteth not onely in filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and deformity, but in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure of evill, it being not onely monſtrous to be lookt upon, but very dangerous and pernicious, which is ſo much the more difficult to bee diſcerned, by how much it
<pb facs="tcp:120697:33"/> ſhrowds it ſelfe under hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call love, and while it beguiles us under the mask of friendſhip, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing I know not what comfort and profit. But if thou wilt prie more narrowly into it, thou ſhalt diſcover it to be no leſſe traiterous unto thee, than was <hi>Joab</hi> unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſa,</hi> who under the vizard of friendſhip ſheathed his ſword in his bowels. Thou ſhalt perceive it to be thy malicious enemy, and ſo much the more to bee feared, by how much it bee more familiar with thee. Thou ſhalt diſcover it to be a ſerpent that thou nouriſheſt in thy boſome, and a viper that thou engendreſt for thy owne deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And I beſeech thee what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort canſt thou pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe thereby, ſeeing it is but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Heare the ſpirit of God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>What hath a man of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and of the vexation of his heart wherein hee hath laboured
<pb facs="tcp:120697:34"/> under the ſunne? For all his dayes are ſorrowes, and his travell griefe; yea, his heart taketh not reſt in the night time. This is alſo vanity.</hi> Eccleſ. 2.22,23. Heare the wife man alſo, who ſaith, <hi>that therein there is no profit,</hi> Eccl. 30.25. It is conducible then neither to thy ſoule nor body, neither furthereth it thy affaires, unleſſe thou enjoyeſt ſome peculiar privilege not affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any one living. Will it reſtore unto thee thy countrey which is now in the power of thy enemies? will it rid thee of thy miſeries? will it deliver thee from injuries and moleſtations? will it performe thy buſineſſe? will it provide or care for thy family? will it pay thy debts? will it proſperouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thee from thy law ſutes? will it extoll thee to honours and dignities? ſhalt thou thereby obtain more health, more ſtrength, more knowledg, more eſteeme, more
<pb facs="tcp:120697:34"/> love? No verily, for future things are not within thy power, and what is paſt cannot be recalled. Go to then thou little miſerable cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe, hide thy ſelfe in ſome corner or other, labour with might and maine, ſearch out all the meanes and occaſions to diminiſh it. Weigh a thouſand and a thouſand times with thy ſelfe the high ſtature of <hi>Goliah,</hi> afflict thy ſelfe as being of a little ſtature, thou wilt never attaine to his.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, all worldly ſorrow is vaine and unprofitable, and would it were onely ſo; thou ſhalt find it grievous and moſt pernicious, unleſſe with ſpeed thou diſchargeſt thy ſelfe there from. Know this, it drawes after it a numerous ſwarme of evils, aſwell corporall as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; as touching temporall evils, it makes mans life altogether miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, infinitly increaſing the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that are the ordinary concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb facs="tcp:120697:35"/> thereof, whether thou conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt his buſineſſes, and counſells, the calamities themſelves, or at laſt his whole perſon. As touching his buſineſſes, it is certaine it diſturbs, yea, overthrowes his beſt and moſt profitable and neceſſary endeavors; It obſcures his mind with innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſad thoughts, which as dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vapours aſcend to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and darkon the cleerneſſe thereof, whence ariſe ſo many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratas or faults diſordering his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and employments, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving him in new difficulties, as wee ſhall preſently make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
               <p>For miſery and afflictions, it augmenteth them five manner of wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it repreſents not calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in their native colours, but ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravates them by what is evill therein increaſing, and what is good depreſſing; ſo that it diſplaies
<pb facs="tcp:120697:35"/> the former which ſhould bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, and conceales the latter which ſhould bee diſcovered; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is the cauſe of many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous calamities which but for it would never happen; for while one by the ſuggeſtion thereof erres manifoldly, it cannot bee but evill and misfortune ſhould befall him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it makes him ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, froward, unaſtable in his converſation, and intollerable to his neighbour, whereby not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome he incurres ſome great cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, whereof King <hi>David</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us a notable example, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.23,4,5,9,7. who having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained victory over his ſonne <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> by whom hee was put off his Kingdome, yet by reaſon of his death he became exceeding ſorry, which uſhered him into a notable errour; for by giving himſelfe to ſorrow, hee neglected his faithfull conſtant and obedient ſubjects, by
<pb facs="tcp:120697:36"/> whoſe magnanimity hee obtained that notable victory, and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Kingdome, and was well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh intangled in new troubles, and like to fall into greater afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then befell him all his life long, even as <hi>Joab</hi> did moſt wiſely warn him, for he was well-nigh forſaken of all his people, and like to loſe his Kingdome, which not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee recoverd. In briefe, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is like a ſpider, which if it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſpin his owne bowels will not ceaſe till it hath woven a whole web of miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it heaps not upon him onely preſent calamities, but draws upon him future miſeries, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would never have fallen out, ſo that he ſtayes not for ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills as come of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, but runs to meet them, and curiouſly and ingeniouſly invents them, for feare whereof he is ſo ſad and penſive, being ignorant that
<pb facs="tcp:120697:36"/> ſufficient to the day is the evill therof, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.34.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, as though thoſe evills, and grievous, reall, and vehement diſcommodities which come of their owne accord, and that by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervall of yeares lodge with us, to wit, loſſe of goods, honours, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſuch as are dear unto us, as alſo baniſhment and impriſonment, did not ſufficiently torment him, he miſerably vexes himſelfe (as hath been ſaid) for ſmall, ſlight, and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous occaſions, which at every moment well-nigh and ordinarily fall out, and are taken hold of the miſerable man with great griefe of mind. Hence it happens, that all his life long well-nigh hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes his owne executioner, being vexed with ſorrow and griefe; whereas if hee would ſet light by ſuch occaſions hee might joyfully paſſe away his life.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, it increaſes the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
<pb facs="tcp:120697:37"/> of this life, in that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeth thoſe bleſſings which God hath conferred upon him, making of them that uſe whereunto they were not deſigned, and cauſeth him to ſet light by all ſuch things as ſhould exhilarate him, or to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, or extenuate Gods benefits conferred upon him, and to take a ſurfet of them, changing all their ſweetneſſe into gall and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood; ſo that it may be compared to that little venemous creature, which turneth the juice of the ſweeteſt flowers into poiſon, or a bad ſtomack by whoſe ill conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the choiſeſt and beſt food is turned into phlegmatick and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full humours. In reſpect of his whole perſon, it brings him into a moſt miſerable condition; for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe in the heart of man makes it ſtoop, and by ſorrow of the heart the ſpirit is broken, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.13. for it corrupts his
<pb facs="tcp:120697:37"/> underſtanding and ſenſes, deprives him of wiſedome, whereby hee is diſabled from attending his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. It makes him to bee a vile abject ſpirit; it ſo blunts the vigor of his mind, as it cannot e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the leaſt degree reſiſt evill; it takes away the inclination of the will to performe any good or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble act redounding to his owne or neighbours good, and renders him uncapable of putting in ure good and profitable employments. In a word, it diſſolves him like pearlin vinegar, neither doth it leſſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the body: for heavineſſe of heart breaketh ſtrength, and a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſpirit drieth the bones, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 38.19. whereupon hee cannot ſleep, or take his reſt in the night time; as may be ſeen in <hi>Antiochus</hi> in whom griefe was more and more, and he made account that he ſhould die; wherefore he called for all his friends, and ſaid unto
<pb facs="tcp:120697:38"/> them, the ſleep is gone from mine eyes, and my heart faileth for very care: in what tribulation am I come, and how great a flood of miſery is it wherein now I am? 1 <hi>Macch.</hi> 6.10.11. It breeds deadly diſeaſes, as is manifeſt in the ſame <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who layed him downe upon his bed, and fell ſicke for griefe, 1 <hi>Macch.</hi> 6,8. hereof comes horineſs and untimely old age. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and wrath ſhortens the life, and carefulneſſe bringeth age before the time, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 30.24. as alſo death, for ſorrow hath kill'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and there is no profit therein, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 30.23. ſaith the wiſe man. And againe, of heavineſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth death, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 38.19. and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, the ſorrow of the world worketh death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. Hereof was the patriarch <hi>Jacob</hi> afraid, as the reſt of his ſons were conveying his ſonne <hi>Benjamin</hi> downe to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> yee ſhall, ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:120697:38"/> he, bring downe my gray haires to the grave with ſorrow, if miſchief befall him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.29. Now of all the effects it produceth, death is the beſt, it being better to die than undergo the continuall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof; death is better than a bitter life, ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 30.17. and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying him, it gives a deadly blow to it ſelfe. The veſſell being broken, the liquor muſt needs run to waſte and periſh, ſo that by his ruine, it being farre more perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious falls to deſtruction. Thus much of the temporall miſeries which attend it; as for ſpirituall evils which are farre more grievous than the former, it is evident, that one through ſorrow doth grievou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly offend God, provoking him to anger through diſobedience, impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, diſtruſt, ingratitude, and brutiſh ſtupidity, which moves God to forſake and leave him
<pb facs="tcp:120697:39"/> wholly to his cares and anxieties, and to ſpeake to him as it were thus, what? doſt thou endeavour through thy carefulneſſe to rob me of the honour, whereby I care for all things; Be it ſo, torment thy ſelfe as long as it pleaſeth thee, thou ſhalt ſee what it will availe thee. Being then left to himſelfe, hee runnes into moſt grievous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities wherein hee is altogether involved by Gods judgement, and by meanes whereof fals into more grievous calamities. It deprives him of the teſtimony of adoption, and the certainty of the right of Gods children; for whoſoever is borne of God overcommeth the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4. But what is it to overcome it? It is not for one to make himſelfe a ſlave thereunto, neither to ſtoop to adverſities on the one ſide, nor to place his felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therein on the other. Hee that doth this may aſſuredly perſwade
<pb facs="tcp:120697:39"/> himſelfe to be borne of God, and to enjoy Gods benevolence and grace, whereby the world is van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. Contrarily one by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſorrowfull, plainly teſtifieth, that he is deſperately in love with this world. Moreover, it openeth a gap to the devill to aſſault him with divers temptations, and bring him into thouſand evills and hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſinnes. The murtherer <hi>Cain</hi> may ſerve for an example, whoſe anger was not onely kindled, but his countenance fell aſſoone as God diſreſpected his ſacrifice, which moved him to kill his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It induces him to become an Apoſtate, or revolter from the true Religion, ſubſcribing and conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the lies of Satan, when ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity is ſet before his view, as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, baniſhment, impriſonment, and death which hee is bound to ſuffer for the confeſſion of truth. It makes him diſpaire, and to lay
<pb facs="tcp:120697:40"/> violent hands upon himſelfe, and miniſtreth an opportunity to the devill to ſet aſide his proper ſhape, and appear unto ſuch as give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereunto viſibly, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in times paſt, which were, as the wiſe man wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, ſcattered under a darke vaile of forgetfulneſſe, being hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly aſtoniſhed and troubled with ſtrange apparitions, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 7.3. It gives way to the envious man the devill to perſwade him to make a covenant with him, and renounce his baptiſme, as witches are wont to doe; which being done, hee poſſeſſeth, vexeth, and tormenteth him after a wonderfull manner. Behold the miſchiefes thereof, behold the off-ſpring the ſorrowfull man breedeth in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome! who ſeeth not, that the grievouſeſt plague is that of the heart, <hi>Eecl.</hi> 25.13. And it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, but it ſhould produce the
<pb facs="tcp:120697:40"/> greateſt mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fortune and miſery, it being the grievouſeſt puniſhment and curſe which God threatneth to the tranſgreſſors of his Law. The Lord ſhall give thee a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of mind, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.65. I will diſtreſſe <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there ſhall be heavineſſe and ſorrow; it ſhall be unto me as <hi>Ariel, Eſay.</hi> 29.2. Thus, ſaith the Lord, of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they ſhall eat their bread with carefulneſſe, <hi>Ez.</hi> 12.19. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move farre from thee this moſt dangerous diſeaſe, and embrace Godly mirth, which, as hath been ſaid, doth not onely become Gods children, but affords excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. It repreſents to the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mans view the happy ſucceſſe of future things, cauſing him to beare all things patiently, and to follow his buſineſſes or employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or forgoe them, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:120697:41"/> to time and other circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And howſoever all things fall not out according to his mind, yet he is contented with his condition. Hee handles worldly things, as they are in their owne nature fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and indifferent; and being not clogg'd by them, he goes on lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily in the way of life, till hee hath proſperouſly finiſhed his journey. Hee leads his life as quietly as hee can in this world, neither aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates it with new miſeries, being burthenſome enough of it ſelfe. His underſtanding is ſound and perfect, in that hee judgeth not according to his affection, but as reaſon directeth him; his body is recreated and refreſhed thereby. Hee knowes experimentally what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes of, a merry heart doth good like a medicine, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.22. A merry heart hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall feaſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.15. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, The gladneſſe of the heart
<pb facs="tcp:120697:41"/> is the life of man, and the joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a man prolongeth his dayes, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 30.22. Moreover, one endued with this ſanctified joy is moſt aſſured of Gods love, and throughly furniſhed againſt Satan, ſo as he cannot exerciſe his power and force upon him. In briefe, the bleſſing of the heavenly father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth upon him, and in that hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth, it is the worke of grace, and becauſe he rejoyceth in God, it is an infallible ſigne that God hath pleaſure in him. Wherefore, be not ſorry for the joy of the Lord is our ſtrength, <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.11. and ſay, I will greatly rejoyce in the Lord, my ſoul ſhall be joyfull in my God, <hi>Eſay</hi> 61.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. The third ground or reaſon why the faithfull man ſhould aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it, and be joyfull, is drawn from Gods ſpirituall grace in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing which ſhould beget a greater meaſure of joy in the faithfull man, than the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and enjoyment of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall benefits which God hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon him; for thereby he is freed from the grievouſneſſe of his miſery, and tranſlated into a moſt happy condition, which thou faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule being in miſery and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which now boils within thee, and is fixed in thy breaſt, ſhouldſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially take into conſideration. That thou maiſt cleerly perceive, as thou oughteſt, Gods grace, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:42"/> judge more rightly of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his benefits, Conſider with me, I beſeech thee, theſe three things, to wit, thy ſtate paſt, preſent, and to come. What is man in reſpect of his paſt eſtate, but naturally the child of wrath and eternall condemnation? for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he was originally created after the image of God, now hee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived thereof by his incredulity and rebellion, which is the cauſe, that by the moſt juſt ſentence of God hee is adjudged to death, that is, to all manner of miſeries, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and corporall, temporall and eternall, wherein hee involved all his poſterity. Hence it is that man is conceived and borne in ſin, and ſo being deprived of righteouſneſſe, he inclines to all vice; his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding darkned, his will maliciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly bent, all his affections depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and out of order. Out of this corrupt fountaine it cannot be, but
<pb facs="tcp:120697:43"/> an infectious and corrupt ſtreame ſhould flow, to wit, perverſe &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable thoughts &amp; words, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the abundance &amp; deprava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his heart, actions altogether unſavory to Gods will. Briefely, he is dead in ſinnes, and ſo curſed in the ſight of God; unto whom that ſpeech of <hi>Martha</hi> may be applied: Lord, by this time he ſtinketh; for he hath beene dead foure dayes, <hi>Jo.</hi> 11.39. for whereas once hee was the temple of God, how he is become a noiſome den and ſinke, whereinto that infernall ſoule diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthens his filth. Nay, hee rebells againſt God, and enters into acts of hoſtility; the wrath of God is thereupon revealed from heaven againſt all his unrighteouſneſſe and ungodlineſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. Being left then to himſelfe by Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he followes his own wayes, he is given to a reprobate ſenſe, whereupon he feeles divers curſes
<pb facs="tcp:120697:43"/> inflicted by God, who either pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth him in his goods, in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in his honours, or in ſuch as are deere unto him; one while hee armes the heaven to be his enemy, otherwhile the Elements, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while beaſts, otherwhile he makes men to fall out amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; At length he cuts him off from the land of the living, whom vengeance dogges no leſſe than before: for his ſoule no ſooner forſakes the body, but it endureth infernall paines untill the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; at what time the body ſhall be re-united to the ſoule, and the whole man tormented with the devill, with horrible, unſpeakable, and eternall torments. The ſtate of that man for miſery ſurpaſſeth infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly the condition of dogs, ſwine, and ſerpents; for theſe beaſts are reduced to nothing, affoon as they expire; Whereas when he is dead his torments begin to act their
<pb facs="tcp:120697:44"/> parts, ſo that what hee ſuffered, or could endure in this world, is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a forerunner, or taſt of thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he muſt undergo after this life. Behold thy firſt genuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſtate wherein God verily might have left thee, and then thou ſhouldeſt moſt miſerably and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally periſh; but hee would not deale ſo ſeverely, but according to the multitude of his mercies had compaſſion upon thee, tranſlating thee into a farre happier condition wherein now thou art. Conſider with me what will afford thee joy and comfort; how happy is thy condition, that whereas God paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by many myriads of men who miſerably periſh for ever, hee hath choſen thee out of his free grace and mercy in Chriſt Jeſus, for which purpoſe it was his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that God ſhould be made man, that the word ſhould bee clothed with an infants nature, and that
<pb facs="tcp:120697:44"/> that heavenly bread, as one of the fathers ſtiles him, ſhould bee made graſſe; for all fleſh is graſſe. Hee would have him firſt to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and incloſed within the wombe of a woman, ere his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power ſhould be diſperſed throughout the whole univerſe by the preaching of the Goſpell; like <hi>Gideons</hi> fleece which was firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed, ere the dew came downe to the plaines. And that through his holineſſe and innocency hee might cover before Gods face our impurity and uncleanneſſe, hee would bee borne of a virgin, and that great with child, not by man but by the Holy Ghoſt: for the Arke was overlayed with pure gold within and without, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.11. And the high prieſt was not to defile himſelfe for his father or for his mother, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21.11. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it behoved him not onely to be borne, but live and die for thee,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:45"/> that thou mightedſt obtaine ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, remiſſion of ſinnes, and righteouſneſſe. And that this might not be fruitleſſe unto thee, hee is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the dead, aſcended into the heavens, and ſitteth on the right of God his heavenly father. And that this alſo might tend to thy good and ſalvation, he hath called thee unto his Church, &amp; made thee a deniſon of that citie, that is ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hill, and ſaith unto thee, as he did once unto <hi>Soul,</hi> ariſe and go to the city, and it ſhall be told thee what thou muſt doe, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6. He found thee in a deſart land, and in the waſte howling wilderneſſe, he made thee ride on the high places of the earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.10.13. and placed thee in the land of uprigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 26.10. hee hath given for food and ſuſtenance his word, that angelicall bread, when others are fed but with the chaſſe and ſtraw of that darkeſome <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120697:45"/> whereunto they are moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably enſlaved; and that thou mighteſt aſſuredly bee perſwaded, that what Chriſt did and ſuffered concerned thee, hee ordained ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments as certaine aſſurances or pledges of his grace. Further, he hath communicated with thee his ſpirit which ſanctifieth thy heart with faith, openeth the eyes of thy underſtanding, wherby thou mayeſt not onely with <hi>Adam</hi> behold thy nakedneſſe, but contemplate his grace; changeth thy will, purifieth thy affections, ſo that not without a miracle thou art renewed into his image, much like that King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was changed into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man; reſtrains thee from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſuch ſins as the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perpretate, &amp; conſequently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth thee from horrible judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and puniſhments due unto the ſame. There redounds unto thee being in the ſtate of grace,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:46"/> honour, felicity, and profit; for what great honour is it to thee to have God for thyfather? what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement is it for thee to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the divine nature in Chriſt, and therein ſuperiour to the Angels themſelves. Hee took not upon him the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of <hi>Abraham, Heb.</hi> 2.13. And that heavenly <hi>Joſeph</hi> had in ſuch eſteeme the worme-eaten ſack of our fleſh, that he vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to put into it the ineſtimable treaſure of our ſalvation. On the other ſide, Angels are but miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth to miniſter for them who ſhall be heires of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. and conſequently for thee in particular. Moreover, what honour is it to be a Prophet, Prieſt, and Prince over all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which ſoveraignty thou haſt purchaſed by Chriſt? ſo that all things are thine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. and appertaine unto thee, which in due
<pb facs="tcp:120697:46"/> time thou ſhalt enjoy, after thou haſt fought in this world the good fight, a plenary poſſeſſion of. The commodities accrewing unto thee in the ſtate of grace are innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for thereby thou art ſhot free from the thunderbolt of the Law, there being no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. And howſoever there be ſome remainder of infirmities in thee, which the fleſh ſinfully puts in practife, yet they are cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the robe of thy eldeſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt; yea, thine owne ſins con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to thy ſalvation, thine own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and the ſenſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity thereof provoking thee to hate them, working in thee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere humility, and inducing thee to behave thy ſelfe for the future more wiſely and warily. Being in the ſtate of grace thou haſt freer acceſſe unto the throne of grace
<pb facs="tcp:120697:47"/> in all thy neceſſities, ſo as thou mayeſt plentifully pour teares into his boſome; hee perſwades thee with precepts, and allures thee with promiſes. His providence leads and preſerves thee as a cloud by day, and the ſhining of a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire by night, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 4.5. He provides thee all neceſſaries that relate to this life, and that which is to come; his Angels are a brazen wall to defend thee. Adde hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that the afflictions themſelves are not ſignes of his wrath, but pledges of his grace and markes of his fatherly care to thy triall and ſpirituall exerciſe, yielding the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.38. Hee is preſent with thee in all temptations and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, ſtrengthning thee by the power of his ſpirit, by whom hee aſcertaines thee of thy eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; perſwading thee, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther death, nor life, nor Angels,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:47"/> nor principalities, nor powers, not things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature ſhall be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thee from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37,38. Whereupon he plants in thy heart ſuch a firme hope of eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, as if thou hadſt already a plenary poſſeſſion thereof; for hope maketh not aſhamed, becauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt which is given us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. Theſe ſpirituall benefits are of that nature, that they will never diminiſh nor faile. Nay, look how much the faithfull man affects them, ſo much the more they increaſe; like to the nurſes milke, which the more it is ſuck'd, the more it abounds. And therefore who ſeeth not, that theſe honours and ſpirituall riches infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly ſurpaſſe all the riches and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this world. This is thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:120697:48"/> condition as long as thou art in this world; as for thy future, thou art indeed, as all men are, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to death, whereby thou ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineſt, more excellent things than thou couldſt injoy in thy life time; ſo that, not without cauſe, it is ſaid, precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.15. for death will put a period unto all thy adverſities, and will be the beginning or rather the fulfilling of all good things. By death thou ceaſeſt to ſinne, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God thy father to anger, and to commit ſuch things, as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy thy eminent condition; as long as thou art clothed with the mantle of fleſh the concupiſcence thereof will vexe and ſolicite thee with that unchaſte woman, ſaying, lie with me; But when thy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as that of <hi>Elias</hi> when he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heaven, ſhall fall from thee, it ſhall never trouble nor
<pb facs="tcp:120697:48"/> moleſt thee. By death thy laſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, all the reſt of thy enemies ſhall be put to flight; They ſhall be never able to hurt and entrap thee. Thou ſhalt be freed from the feare of all dangers which in this life abide thee. It will rid thee from all moleſtations, milteries, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, cares, and griefes. Thy foule being ſevered from thy body will eſcape, as a bird out of the ſnare of the fouler; the ſnare is broken and wee are eſcaped, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.7. Being then freed from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable torments, and troubles, ſhe ſhall enter into reſt; inſomuch, that when the laſt houre ſhall make the neereſt approach, thou mayeſt ſay unto her, Return unto thy reſt O my ſoule, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7. Departing this world, ſhe ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into heaven to injoy eternall happineſſe, and rejoyce at the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall viſion of her heavenly
<pb facs="tcp:120697:49"/> bridegoome. Then ſhee goeth forth to behold King <hi>Solomon</hi> with the Crowne, wherewith his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crowned him in the day of his eſpouſals, and in the day of the gladneſſe of his heart, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.11. As for thy body, it ſhall returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to duſt, but it ſhall not long remain in that ſtate. It is ſown verily in corruption, it is raiſed in incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is ſown in diſhonour, it is raiſed in power, it is a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42,43,44. ſo that the death of the body is nothing elſe, but as feed caſt into the earth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing in its time moſt plentifull fruit: Then being reunited to the ſoule ſhall bee brought into the Kings chambers, where it will bee glad, and rejoyce for ever, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy plenary poſſeſſion of ineffable happineſſe, which eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, neither have entred into the heart of man the
<pb facs="tcp:120697:49"/> things which God hath prepared for them that love him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Goe to then, if thy condition hath beene ſo miſerable, and will bee ſo happy, haſt not thou ſufficient cauſe to rejoyce? Now thou art ſorrowfull, and deſpaireſt, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereſt moleſtations which thou canſt not repell or drive away from thee, repeating theſe words to thy ſelfe, Alas! when will that day appeare wherein I ſhall have cauſe of rejoycing, and rendring thanks to God. Know this, that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of ſpirituall benefits were there no other occaſion moving thee to rejoyce ſhould bee a moſt weighty motive inducing thee thereunto, and even without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to praiſe God amidſt the moſt grievous calamities. How would that wretched Captive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, being ſet at liberty from the darke and noyſome dungeon? with what exultation did that lame man,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:50"/> reſtored to his feet by <hi>Peter,</hi> praiſe God, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.8. The guilty perſon being certified of his Princes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, even at the very nick hee is to ſuffer, for joy is as it were wrapt out of himſelf. Judge thou whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the miſeries of this world may bee compared to that, out of which God hath rid thee. Canſt thou be ſo ſenceleſſe and dull, as not to rejoyce from the bottome of thy heart, in that he hath delivered thee from thoſe infinite calamities, thoſe everlaſting burnings and darkneſſe where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth? Thou art really poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thou haſt a moſt juſt cauſe to be ſorrowfull, and conclude thy condition to bee miſerable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy. Then verily thou ſhouldſt have cauſe to complaine of thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, if God had left thee in the ſtate of corruption and miſery. Alas! how many miſerable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are there, and will bee in hell,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:50"/> who have knowne neither good nor evill? And how many are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who though they lived in this world without the feare of God, yet committed not ſuch grievous ſinnes as thou didſt, and thought they worſhipped God aright? But ſince they lived without faith, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made Gods will revealed in his word a rule to ſquare their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by, were ſons of perdition. And could not God leave thee in the very ſame miſery hee left them in by his juſt judgement? Conſider then how much happier thou art then ſo many Miriads of men who are eternally damned. Conſider further, how farre happier thou art than innumerable wicked men, who whileſt they lived in this world were ſeemingly bleſſed, in regard of honours, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, powers, eſtimation, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. How infinitly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compariſon is thy condition
<pb facs="tcp:120697:51"/> happier than their ſtate in that they perſiſting in their ſinnes are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to horrible puniſhments and unutterable torments? God forbid then thou ſhouldſt envy their var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing happineſſe and deceitfull proſperity, and that thou wilt not conſider how much happier thou art than thoſe as being not liable to the ſame condemnation. And if thou canſt not find in thy heart to be joyfull, in that hee hath not left thee in that miſerable plight; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thou haſt a more weighty motive thereunto, in that hee hath tranſlated thee into a moſt happy condition, vouchſafing to receive thee into the number of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; for he is not onely ſatisfied to deliver thee from ſo many evils, but he ſends thee as many benefits. That ſpeech of Chriſt unto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples concerns thee; Rejoyce, that your names are written in heaven, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20. Thou wouldſt really
<pb facs="tcp:120697:51"/> rejoyce, if thou wert now in the ſtate of innocency, wherein <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was in that earthly paradiſe; but aſſure thy ſelfe, there is greater than paradiſe here. For thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveſt more bleſſings and honours in Chriſt, than thou haſt loſt in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> Then man was Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, now thou art his ſonne in Chriſt. The firſt man was formed out of earthly matter, thou art borne of heavenly and incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeed, Gods word. In thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate thou couldſt ſin, as that dolefull experience witneſſeth: In this, thou canſt not ſinne. In that thou wert ſubject to die, whereas the life prepared for thee in Chriſt hath neither end nor conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Laſtly, doth not the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thy future condition move thee to rejoyce? The time will ſhortly appeare wherein all thy adverſities and miſeries ſhall be brought to a period, and thou
<pb facs="tcp:120697:52"/> ſhalt poſſeſſe all thoſe things which God hath prepared for thee, and enter into that joy which cannot be taken from thee. The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſay of thy preſent, paſt, and future condition ſhould induce thee to bee contented with that ſtate and ſtation which God hath allotted thee. Let others rejoyce, that they are rid and recovered from ſome dangerous diſeaſe, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, or ſome other adverſity wherewith thou art now poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Thou haſt through Gods grace eſcaped thouſand dangers, and miſeries, which without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon ſurpaſſe all the calamities of this world. Let others boaſt in the multitude of their riches, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wax proud of their gay ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell and dignities; what are all theſe things compared with the Majeſty of the child of God, and coheire with Jeſus Chriſt? Let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers feed themſelves with vaine
<pb facs="tcp:120697:52"/> hopes, that of glory and future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe will never give thee the lurch; wherefore take heed of murmuring againſt God, beware thou ſayeſt at any time, that hee deales ſeverely with thee. Doth he deale ſeverely with thee, who hath conferred upon thee ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, who heapeth upon thee ſo many benefits? doth hee deale roughly with thee, who reſerves for thee for the time to come ſuch ample felicitie? Let that ſpeech therefore of our Saviour to Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſound continually in thy eares, or rather in thy heart, my grace is ſufficient for thee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. and in all adverſities which daily happen in this world, ſeeke eaſe, refreſhment, and comfort, by contemplating Gods grace; for a Kings favour, I ſay, the King of Kings favour is as dew upon the ground, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The fourth ground or reaſon conſiſts in the corporall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits conferred by God.</head>
               <p>THe ineffable dignity of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall grace, as hath been ſaid, ſhould bee juſt cauſe to remove from thee ſorrow, wherewith thou art poſſeſſed. But wee have not as yet mentioned all Gods benefits beſtowed upon thee, his grace and goodneſſe reſting not in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned benefits, but tending and extending themſelves further; for with his right hand of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all benefits he imbraceth thee, his left of temporall being under thy head; ſo that thou haſt experience of what the ſpouſe of Chriſt wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth to her ſelfe, ſaying, His left
<pb facs="tcp:120697:53"/> hand ſhould bee under my head, and his right hand ſhould embrace mee, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.3. Neither is hee ſatisfied to quicken thee with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life, and provide thee food and rayment, as alſo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with thee unſpeakable bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and honours, but hee goeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he deales with thee as a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving earthly father doth with his children in their minority, ſuffering them to play, and uſe all manner of ratles that they may with more pleaſure paſſe away their infancy. Thy heavenly father deales no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with thee, for he beſtows upon thee ſo many temporall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, the ſweetneſſe whereof ſhould exhilarate thee and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that bitterneſſe of ſpirit which now pines thee away. The benefits that thou enjoyeſt are of two ſorts: ſome particular, ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called, which howſoever ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe enjoy, yet they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb facs="tcp:120697:54"/> upon each ſingular perſon, and ſome common which concern all that can read this little book; ſo that none hath cauſe to complain, or caſt an envious eye upon his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hath God, I beſeech thee, more eſpecially honored thee than an infinite multitude of men? Art thou perchance through his grace ſprouted out of a royall, illuſtrious; famous, noble ſtock, or at leaſt of an honeſt family, or neerly allied thereunto? As for thy calling and ſtate, God perchance hath ſingled thee out to be a leader and King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his people, and ſubjected to thy empire and power nations, and choſen thee to bee his vicegerent and aſſiſtant here on earth; or art in the number of the Gods? that is to ſay, a magiſtrate, to diſtribute judgement and juſtice to thoſe that are committed to thy charge, to protect the innocent, defend the widow, orphan, and ſtranger, to
<pb facs="tcp:120697:54"/> condemne the guilty and puniſh the evill doer. In briefe, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance hee hath given thee that honour whereby many are become ſubject unto thee. But if thy fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction bee not politicall, God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance hath conſtituted thee to be Chriſts ſteward in his houſe, the Church, to diſtribute to his family heavenly food, to preach his word, to be an overſeer of his flock, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eminent honour and good work, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks; or art per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of ſome other honeſt calling? as employed in merchandiſe, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorſhip, or ſome other lawfull occupation; or art of good odour through Gods favour not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thy owne Countrey-men, but amongſt forreiners, in reſpect of magnanimity, ſtrength, vertue, wiſdome, or learning? for a good report maketh the bones fat, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.30. Becauſe he that is in good eſteeme reapeth pleaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.
<pb facs="tcp:120697:55"/> And therefore a good name is father to bee choſen than great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1. Or hath hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver &amp; above theſe things beſtow'd upon thee the goods of this world, commonly ſo called? to wit, riches, commodities, lands, poſſeſſions, vineyards, fields, houſes, or the like bleſſings which continually hee poures upon thee. And if thy yearly revenues be not anſwerable to thy will, God like that good <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb</hi> deales with thee; for after he hath given thee barren land, hee gives thee the upper, and nether ſprings, <hi>Judg.</hi> 1.15. hee bleſſeth thy labours and employments; for thou ſhalt eat the labours of thy hands, O well is thee, and happy ſhalt thou be, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.2. And hee filleth thee with the fineſt wheat, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.14. Hee gives thee not onely ſo much as ſufficed the Apoſtle, to wit, food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which will nouriſh thee,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:55"/> and thy family, but hee beſtowes upon thee more than thy neceſſities require, yea, oftentimes in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; ſo that he deales graciouſly with thee, ſo as thou mayeſt not onely live without penury and want, but ſuccour thy poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with almes proportionable to thy power, aſwell to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Gods glory, as to the good of thy countrey. Hee communicates with thee riches and meanes, whereby thou mayeſt not onely bring up thy children in good and honeſt diſcipline and ſciences, but eſpecially in the feare of God, advancing them to bee thy equalls in dignity, or to a higher pitch of honour, leaving them after thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe in ſuch ſort, as they bee not conſtrained to depend upon other mens mercies, or compelled by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty to want education, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come miſerable men. Or hath hee bleſſed thee in a happy matrimony,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:56"/> by joyning thee to a meet helpe, I mean thy bedfellow, no leſſe fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full than honourable, inriched with divers endowments of the body, but eſpecially thoſe of the ſoule, vertue, wiſdome, ſtayedneſſe, and modeſty? Or hath hee made thee a father or mother to a family, ſo that thy wife is as a fruitfull vine by the ſides of thine houſe, thy children like olive plants round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy table. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.3. Or are they ſtrong in body and ſound in underſtanding? increaſing in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dayly before thy eyes, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the feare of God, as tender plants of Gods garden; And doe they profit by thy inſtructions, chaſtiſements, and corrections, yeelding thee comfortable hope for the future? Or are they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vane'd to ſome degree of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be pillars of thy old age? Or ſeeſt thou thy childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? or to ſpeak in a word, art
<pb facs="tcp:120697:56"/> partaker of that divine bleſſing, whereof the ſpirit of God ſpeaks, who ſo findeth a good wife, findeth a good thing, and obtaineth favour of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.22. Or art one of thoſe whom the Holy Ghoſt ſtiles bleſſed, in the Pſalme above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned? I paſſe over in ſilence the externall delights thou haſt of thy children, eſpecially during their minority. I will onely touch one, and a ſingular one too, whereby they repreſent the lively image of Gods true children, even as may be ſeen in ſuch actions as thou perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt towards thy children, the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſentation of Gods govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ordering his; for know this, there is no action, inclination, humour, defect, vice, or perfection which thou findeſt in thy children, but expreſſe a faithfull man to the life, either in goodneſſe or vice; ſo that thou canſt not obſerve even the leaſt appearance of them in thy
<pb facs="tcp:120697:57"/> children, but thou art conſtrained to acknowledge that Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren behave themſelves no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to their heavenly father, and neighbours. And contrarily, thou canſt not aſcribe any thing thing to a wiſe prudent father, but muſt confeſſe that God obſerves the ſame order and government to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his children, which is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly an excellent prerogative which married perſons, and ſuch as God hath bleſſed with children, enjoy; a prerogative, I ſay, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſuch as want iſſue, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe that forbid others to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and keep themſelves unmarried, are devoyd, and thereby are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of wholeſome knowledge, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, comfort, which married perſons enjoy in regard of the fruitfulneſſe of marriage divinely bleſſed, and infants unto whoſe ſchoole our Saviour ſends us. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I ſay unto you (ſaith he) except
<pb facs="tcp:120697:57"/> yee bee converted, and become as little children, yee ſhall not enter into the kingdome of Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. Thus much of the benefits, which concerne thy whole perſon: Now let us view the parts, whereof man is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And in the firſt place the ſoul, What a gracious benefit is it, that God hath endued thee with a good wit, a quick penetrating un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſtrong judgement, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent memory, prudence and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity in performing thy employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and foreſeeing good and bad events, wherby thou takeſt heed from innumerable errours, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into ſuch as are inprovident, and thoſe that are careleſſe in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires runne, and ſo become miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable men? Or hath God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance imparted unto thee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſciences, or ſuch a facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whereby thou canſt diſcharge thy mind with ſit expreſſions? or
<pb facs="tcp:120697:58"/> hath hee endued thee with a noble generous ſpirit, ſo as thou art mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous in all diſtreſſes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danted in all dangers? Adde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a merry heart, and quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented mind, which according to the Proverb is better than riches; and by the teſtimony of the Holy Ghoſt, godlineſſe with content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is great gaine. As touching the body, what a gracious benefit is it, that hee hath cloathed thee with perfect members without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault; neither lame nor maimed, but ſtrong, endued with good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, diſpoſition, proportion, and decent beauty? What a precious treaſure is health, which he either preſerves or reſtores unto thee. All which benefits certainly are excellent, and whereof ſome are ineſtimable, which evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by ſuch evils as are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to thoſe benefits that thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeſt: for what a heart-burning
<pb facs="tcp:120697:58"/> would poſſeſſe thee, I beſeech thee, if thou wert accurſed of all men, or a reproach and laughing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke? what miſery is there in poverty, and eſpecially in begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? what anguiſh of heart would torment thee, if all things in thy family were turned topſie turvie; if thy marriage bed were defiled, or if thou ſhouldſt find therein nought ſave ſterility and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? if thy children were defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in body, voyd of reaſon, and common ſenſe, and of untoward diſpoſition, throwing themſelves headlong into miſchiefes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently thee to the grave? what unhappineſſe would it bee if thou wert ſtupid, ſenceleſſe, fooliſh, light, impetuous, brutiſh, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, heady, vile, abject, whereby ſo many men and families are quite undone? And was it not in his power to create thee ſo, and in the beginning forme thee imperfect,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:59"/> maimed, monſtrous, blind, deafe, dumbe, filthy, or otherwiſe defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive? And could hee not make ſome noyſome diſeaſe to bee thy individuall aſſociate? yea, cannot he at this inſtant faſten thee to thy bed, and ſo deprive thee of health, which thou haſt ſo many manner of wayes abuſed? By confidering theſe evils (to paſſe by other cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, my purpoſe being to touch thoſe that be contrary to the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned benefits) thou canſt not ſufficiently eſteeme the value of ſuch benefits as God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon thee. Who can number all the good things received at his hands? The earth is full of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.24. and his mercies are new every morning, <hi>La.</hi> 3.23. which is more, thou haſt not received as yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance all the temporall benefits which God reſerves for thee in his treaſure, which as farre as thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb facs="tcp:120697:59"/> requires thou ſhalt enjoy in due time. But thou wilt ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, ſome or many of thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits wee have mentioned are denied thee, yea, cleane contrary, thou art afflicted with ſome of the miſeries above-mentioned, and which is more, all manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities have made a conſpiration againſt thee; thou art ſo farre off from obteining thoſe divine bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, that thou art in contempt and driven to poverty, yea, to beggery, that thou haſt not a wife corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to thy will, that thou art unhappy in thy children, that thou art voyd of wit, rude, ignorant, fearefull; In briefe, that od hath not given thee any of his temporall benefits, and therefore haſt no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to rejoyce, but perpetually to be ſorrowfull. I anſwer, firſt it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or ſeldome falls out, that any man is generally deveſted of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits; but moſtly if this or that be
<pb facs="tcp:120697:60"/> wanting, hee is ſupplied in ſome other benefit. If thou haſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of riches, God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched thee with a contented mind, with knowledge of the moſt excellent things; thou art in good eſtimation, and God hath given thee beautifull children, health, wiſdome, and ſtrength; what will a wiſe man doe in this caſe, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he will not reſpect what hee is deſtitute of, but what hee poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and ſo putting ſorrow to flight hee will rejoyce in the Lord. Secondly, put caſe God hath not beſtowed upon thee any of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-mentioned benefits, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thee with the repugnant evils; yet this is moſt certaine, that hee hath conferred upon thee no leſſe evident and excellent benefits, I meane thoſe which (as hath beene ſaid) in the beginning of this Chapter are common to all, and thou canſt not deny, but thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:120697:60"/> received, and doeſt yet enjoy. But it is a lamentable thing to ſee, that common benefits are not valued but ſlighted by fooles, which dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates nothing from their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; ſince it is uſuall, that the moſt precious and excel ent things, as being daily obvious, are deſpiſed or at leaſt not regarded. What is there, I beſeech thee, more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull than the Sunne? What is more wonderfull than its motion? What more uſefull than the light therof? yet notwithſtanding how few there bee that have the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency thereof in a deſerved eſteem, conſidering not the end whereunto it was deſigned, to wit, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and glory of God. What is more neceſſary to nouriſh and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine us than bread? yet becauſe God gives it us daily, we make not of it ſuch eſteem as we ought; ſo there bee many things wee begin then to value, when we are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:120697:61"/> thereof, and underſtand wee can in no wiſe ſtand in need of them. The reaſon is the ſame of ſuch benefits as God conferres up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men, whereof if they were deſtitute, would be of all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures moſt miſerable; but they that enjoy them, in the feare of God, may thinke themſelves happy, though particular benefits be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as it pleaſeth God. For I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, how gracious is God herein, that hee hath not created thee a ſerpent, toad, or the like crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but after his owne image, communicating with thee his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which with the divine and angelicall is ſolely capable of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe? Hee compoſed thee of a ſoule and body, whoſe conjunction is divine, a very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent miracle, yea, one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that thou canſt conceive in thy mind. Hee hath faſhioned thee in thy mothers wombe, ſo as thou
<pb facs="tcp:120697:61"/> mayeſt ſay with <hi>David,</hi> I will praiſe thee, O God, for I am fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and wonderfully made. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous are thy workes, and that my ſoule knoweth right well. My ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance was not hid from thee, when I was made in ſecret, and curiouſly wrought in the loweſt parts of the earth: Thine eyes did ſee my ſubſtance, yet being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.14,15,16. He hath endued thee with reaſon, and common ſenſe, whereby thou may eſt diſcerne good from bad, and therefore hee ranked thee not in the number of fooles, as hee might, who are ſpectacles to all men, being comedies to ſome, but tragedies to good and wiſe men. What a pleaſant ſpectacle is it for thee to act thy part upon the brave Theatre of this world, wherein thou ſeeſt ſo many Characters of Gods power that may raviſh thy mind? For if the ſight of a peece
<pb facs="tcp:120697:62"/> of work curiouſly wrought doth ſo raviſh the beholders, haſt thou not cauſe, I beſeech thee, to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate with more aſtoniſhment, and delight, this wonderfull univerſe, this round ball, that azurd heaven beſpangled with ſo many glittering ſtarres? What is more wonderfull and pleaſant to the ſight than the Sunne, which is as a bridegroome comming out of his chamber, and rejoyceth as a ſtrong man to runne his courſe? His going forth is from the end of the heaven, and his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits unto the ends of it, and there is nothing hid from the heat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29 5,6. What a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſight doth the nocturnall ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall motion of the Moone exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, which by wonderfull mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is one while ſeene under this or that forme, and ſometimes not at all? Adde hereunto the ſpacious firmament under heaven, which ſerves for our reſpiration or brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
<pb facs="tcp:120697:62"/> the vaſt ſea, and the earth poiz'd with its own weight, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not without a ſtupendio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the midſt of the air, where no prop ſupports it, but only the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull hand of the Almighty; and ſo many ſorts of riches within the bowels of the earth, and on the flouriſhing furface thereof; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinds of living creatures in the aire, water, and on the earth, whereof ſome are pleaſant to the eye, ſome deformed, ſome for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and profit, and ſome for bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. If a tragedy or comedy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but mans invention, acted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtage doth ſo raviſh the eies and mind of the ſpectators, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe the innumerable ſpectacles thou ſeeſt in this world, I meane Gods judgement, which one while ſpeaks his goodneſſe and patience, and otherwhile his wrath, ſhould excite thee to praiſe his goodneſſe and divine juſtice. In briefe,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:63"/> whereſoever thou wilt caſt thine eyes ſhalt have reaſon to crie out with the Prophet, Lord thou haſt made me glad through thy workes, and thy thoughts are very deep; an unwiſe man doth not conſider this, and a foole doth not underſtand it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.5,6,7. How bountifull is God herein, that hee hath given thee nouriſhment all thy life long, &amp; eſpecially in thy mothers womb, whereas thou haſt not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſame, ſo for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement thereof didſt not care? And no ſooner thou cameſt into this world, but the ſame nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ready at hand for thee in thy mothers paps, which as thou didſt ignorantly ſeek for, ſo didſt readily find out. Al this is ſo ſtrange and wonderfull that thou couldſt not ſcarce believe the beginning of thy life to bee ſuch, unleſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were thy daily teachers, ſo as thou mayeſt ſay, and not unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:63"/> Lord, out of the mouth of Babes and ſucklings thou haſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſtrength, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 8.2. Moreover, the very ſame God hath preſerved thee from that time till this preſent, ſtrengthning thy ſtaffe of life, bleſſing thy portion. To which end hee gave thee not onely the herbs of the earth, but the beaſts of the fields, the ſoules of the ayre, and the fiſhes of the ſea. Hee provides for thee being oftentimes driven to ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as thou haſt not food ſufficient for a day, eſpecially in the time of ſearſuy and famine, even in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected time; yea, ſometimes after a wonderfull manner, ſo that thou haſt perſonall experience that God feedeth the hungry, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.7. Is this a ſlender benefit, that he hath preſerved thee from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, which is the moſt raging e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and more grievous than any puniſhment whatſoever? And how
<pb facs="tcp:120697:64"/> gracious is God herein, that hee doth not onely nouriſh thee, but cloath thee alſo with rayment, whereby thou mayeſt not onely cover thy nakedneſſe, but protect thy ſelfe againſt the injuries of the aire, and diſcommodities, moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, paines, which the leaſt flie were able to doe thee. But if this doth ſeeme a ſmall benefit, behold a poore naked wretch who hath not wherewith to cover his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and conſider the miſeries whereunto hee is expoſed. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der further, what ſingular care hee took of thee all thy life long, for aſſoone as hee brought thee into this world hee forſook thee not, as Architects are wont to doe; who aſſoone as they finiſh their work, have not from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the leaſt care of the ſame. But when thy father and mother forſakes thee the Lord taketh thee up, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh, by
<pb facs="tcp:120697:64"/> day his cloud protects thee, and by night his pillar of fire defendeth thee. In all manner of adverſities, dangers, and difficulties he helpeth thee, when thou art aſleep expoſed to thouſand dangers, which thou canſt not even in the leaſt degree withſtand, thy ſences locked up, thy body being as it were dead, when thou takeſt thus thy eaſe and repoſe hee watcheth over thee, and his Angels keep a ward about thee. Hee kept thee as the apple of his eye, as an Eagle ſtirreth up her neſt, fluttereth over her young, ſpreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them, beareth them on her wings; ſo the Lord alone did lead thee, and there was no ſtrange god with him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.10,11,12. And doth this ſeeme a ſmall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, that hee hath ruled and directed thy thoughts, words, and actions, from thy beginning till this preſent time? Hath hee not oftentimes
<pb facs="tcp:120697:65"/> ſuggeſted unto thee moſt excellent thoughts, infuſed in thee good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, put in thy mouth good words, and given thee whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome counſells, and moved thee to performe ſuch actions as have beene profitable to thy ſelfe, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and oftentimes to the whole ſtate and Church of Chriſt; and oftentimes hee hath ſtirred up in thee good motions and inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even beſides thy intention and purpoſe, whereby thou haſt ſpoken and acted many things, which if thou wert now to re-iterate couldſt at no hand performe; ſo that thou haſt experience of that of <hi>David,</hi> O Lord, thou haſt ſearched mee, and knowne mee, thou knoweſt, &amp;c. Thou compaſeſt my path, and my lying downe, and art acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all my wayes, for there is not a word in my tongue, but loe thou knoweſt it altogether. Thou haſt ſet mee behind and before and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:65"/> layed thine hand upon mee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.1,2,3,4,5. Conſider, that he ſaith there is not a word in my tongue, &amp;c. whereby thou mayſt know, that thoſe good things that ever befell thee proceeded not at all from thine owne counſell and prudence. And as often as thou haſt purpoſed to commit any thing, that might endanger thy ſalvation, and blemiſh thy reputation, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth thee from putting the ſame in practice, as hee with-held King <hi>Gerar</hi> from touching <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> wife, and ſinning againſt him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.6. And thus he permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee not to commit ſuch a crime, as deſerves to bee expiated with a reproachfull puniſhment in the ſight of the Sunne. Or if thou art guilty thereof; O! how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull is his goodneſſe and long ſuffering, in that he hath delivered thee from puniſhment due unto the ſame; whereas others, which are
<pb facs="tcp:120697:66"/> not ſuch great delinquents are hanged or drowned, or end their miſerable infamous life in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puniſhment. And to whom do al thoſe gracious benefits apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, whereof thou complaineſt art deprived, and which God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributes unto others, to wit, riches, honours pleaſures, dignities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and the goods of the mind and the body? art not thou parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker thereof by the benefit of the communion of the Saints? for what things ſoever thou ſeeſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to enjoy, are common to thee wee, being all members of the ſame body, whereby we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come partakers of the benefits aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as of the miſeries of others. It behoves thee therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce for the proſperitie of thy neighbour, and with him to thank the father of lights from whom commeth every good gift, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Saint <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſheth thee,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:66"/> when he ſaith, Rejoyce with them that rejoyce, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all theſe benefits which God hath conferred upon thee, Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I beſeech thee, from what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and misfortunes hee hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved thee: There is no calamity whereunto thou art not expoſed, for thy body is a ſeminary of all diſeaſes, from without all manner of adverſities lie in wait for thee, the devill never leaves off his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, the whole world, all the elements, nay all the creatures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt thee by reaſon of ſin. What treacheries doe the wicked alwayes, thine enemies, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Gods, imagine againſt thee? How often have they gone about to rob thee of thy honour, goods, and life it ſelfe? whereſoever thou art death purſues thee at thy heels, all things are every where malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and to bee feared of thee. In briefe, all the evils and perils un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:120697:67"/> the cope of heaven levell at thy deſtruction, ſo that thou ſhouldſt not thinke it ſtrange if being in danger of ſo many wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and blowes thou now and then feeleſt ſome ſmart, but count it no ſmall favour, that many fell in vaine, and that all manner of adverſities have not ruſhed upon thee with one aſſault, and ſay with the Prophet, It is of the Lords mercies that wee are not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe his compaſſions faile not, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22. for his mercy is evident herein, that hee hath not, nor will never ſuffer all manner of evils to make a ſport of thee, for hee is ſo mercifull, that hee will not ſuffer thee to bee tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thy ſtrength: And when hee ſendeth ſome adverſity, hee viſiteth thee onely with one or two evils, and that not daily, but ſometimes, and by intervals, that it may not be perpetuall, but continue for a time,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:67"/> which will not laſt at the furtheſt longer than this life, but ſhall have the ſame period therewith, which in compariſon of eternity deſerves not to be ſtiled a moment. Moreover, if thou conſidereſt the nature and quality of thoſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that God ſends upon thee, hee ſpares and deales mildly, nay father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with thee; for hee permitteth thee not to be as miſerable as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who though they are men crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after his owne image, aſwell as thou, yet lie groveling in ſtewes, upon the high-wayes, and by the doores of Churches, whoſe faces and noſes are eaten up, and whoſe eyes are wanting, and other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers conſumed by ſome foule, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, diſeaſe, or are otherwiſe moſt miſerably afflicted with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary calamity, whom thou canſt not paſſe by for very horrour, but wilt turne away thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from them. Not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:120697:68"/> other evils, beſides thoſe moſt grievous calamities they endure in this life, and perchance eternall puniſhment of hell-fire hereafter. Could not God deale with thee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner? for thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveſt not lighter, but more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous puniſhments than thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy men. I ſay nothing of the tragicall ends of ſo many men, who perchance were leſſe blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than thou, or ſome notable thiefe, or an unclean adulterer, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom God out of his long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and patience, grants a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er terme of life, either thereby to invite him to repentance, or draw him thereunto, as being one of his choſen veſſels; when as others, guilty perchance of leſſer crimes, are miſerably cut off from the Land of the living. Moreover, he preſerves thee not only from thoſe miſeries whereunto others are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, whereof thou mayeſt doubt
<pb facs="tcp:120697:68"/> whether they bee of the ranke of Gods children; but he deales more mildly with thee, than with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, whom thou knoweſt to bee his deareſt children, to wit, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, and a grand cloud both of ancient and moderne witneſſes, which were ſubject to moſt ſharp, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven horrible trials, and burnt, and expoſed to the jawes and clawes of wild beaſts, and to other moſt exquiſite torments; ſo that what now grieves thee is little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing compared to what they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: they, I ſay, who for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and excellency went infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyond thee. Adde hereunto the calamities which ſo many of the faithfull ſuffered, during theſe laſt warres, wherein ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, yea, miriads of godly men, periſhed in a miſerable manner, and are as yet conſumed without regard of age, ſexe, and condition.
<pb facs="tcp:120697:69"/> That I ſay nothing now that God hath preferved thee from thoſe and ſuch like epidemicall evils, to wit, the plague and famine, which have made a ſore ſlaughter amongſt the faithfull. But what doe I ſay? hee freed thee not onely from ſuch calamities as many of the faithfull endured, but his goodneſſe and mercy extendeth further: for if thou commeſt to the mountaine of <hi>Myrrhe</hi> ſhalt ſee Chriſt Jeſus the well-beloved and onely begotten ſonne of his father, who hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered infinit times more than thou or any mortall man could endure. He drank up even the whole cup of Gods wrath, which no man living could doe. I have ſpoken enough of Gods unſpeakable bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and grace, whereby hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected thee from an innumerable troope of miſeries, that they could not ſet upon thee. His goodneſſe reſts not here, for hee hath preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:120697:69"/> thee not onely from ſuch a floud of miſeries which would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelme thee, but hee rids thee out of infinit adverſities that have aſſaulted thee. What evils, mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, diſtreſſes and afflictions haſt thou been ſubject unto, ſince thou cameſt from thy mothers wombe? How often haſt thou fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len one while through thine owne fault, imprudence, fooliſhneſſe, and another while through other mens wickedneſſe and inconſideration, into moſt grievous perils? Canſt thou, I beſeech thee, call to mind how many afflictions thou haſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped? Which of theſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wouldſt thou chuſe, to return againe to thy infancy, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the ſame, or at this inſtant give up the Ghoſt? who would not, if in his right mind, embrace the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, rather than the former. The nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe evills being ſo many, their diverſitie ſo wonderfull, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:70"/> their weight ſo intollerable. But behold, thou art by Gods grace rid of them all. Thou haſt ſhot the gulph of afflictions; thou returneſt a conquerour from thoſe conflicts, ſo that thou haſt perſonall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that which God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the Prophet, When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee, and through the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, they ſhall not overflow thee; when thou walkeſt through the fire thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee, <hi>Eſay,</hi> 43.2. Take into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thy life paſt, and thou ſhalt have cauſe to ſay with joy, he hath brought me out of the horrible pit, and ſet my feet upon the rocks, and ordered my goings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.2. Thus much of thoſe benefits which thy heavenly father hath graciouſly conferred upon thee and canſt not deny but haſt received. Thou ſeeft here, as in a little table,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:70"/> Gods infinit benefits and bleſſings beſtowed upon thee; a table not fleightly to bee viewd, I ſay, but that thou mayeſt feed thine eyes in beholding it, and tickle thine eares in hearing the contents thereof, and applie it, as thou oughteſt, to thine owne ſelfe. And whilſt thy mind is contemplating theſe things, firſt of all, haſt thou not cauſe to render thanks unto the Lord for ſo many temporall benefits, and to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all thy thoughts, words, and actions, &amp; to ſay with <hi>Jacob,</hi> O God of my fathers, I am not worthy of the leaſt of all thy mercies, &amp; of all the truth which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy ſervant? and with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> What ſhall I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto the Lord? I will take up the cup of ſalvation, and call upon the name of the Lord now in the preſence of all his people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.13,14. Further, ſeeing that thou haſt received through Gods grace
<pb facs="tcp:120697:71"/> and ample bountifulneſſe ſo many benefits, and doſt yet enjoy, haſt thou not cauſe to take them all into conſideration, thereby to oppoſe them unto ſorrow, and rejoyce in the Lord? As often therefore as calamity, griefe, ſorrow, ſhall ſeize upon thee, call to mind forthwith thoſe benefits, and ſay, I am at this preſent afflicted with adverſity, diſcommodities oppreſſe mee, I feele affliction and griefe, but on the other ſide I rejoyce in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold benefits he hath hitherto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon me, and ſay withall, is it fit and meete, that this preſent affliction ſhould ſo torment mee with ſorrow, and that ſo many bleſſings, being ſo many pledges of Gods favour, which I have, and daily doe enjoy, ſhould not move me to be joyfull? God forbid; if there be any one thing that might move me to bee ſorrowfull, there be more things ſhould exhilarate
<pb facs="tcp:120697:71"/> me, unleſſe I would by being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull play the traitor againſt divine Majeſtie. As for the griefe and moleſtations which oppreſſe me, what are they compared to ſo many benefits, that I have, and dayly doe enjoy? Why ſhould it grieve me to take them as ſauce, to temper the ſweetneſſe of benefits which elſe would be diſtaſtfull, and draw mee to a ſurfet? It is our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that unleſſe God temper his benefits with afflictions, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with them; and unleſſe he viſiteth us with adverſities, we would procure them to our ſelves, and that to our utter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. The fiſt ground or reaſon is drawne from Gods providence, and that the faithfull man ſhould for the future hope to receive corporall benefits.</head>
               <p>GOds grace reſts not here, but goeth further; for it ſufficeth not him onely to beſtow upon thee till this preſent houre ſo many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefits, being ſo many pledges of his goodneſſe, but hee wills his favour ſhould continue towards thee for the future, and that through his fatherly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, wiſedome, goodneſſe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and help, whereby he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeth all thy employments, and hath continuall care in providing
<pb facs="tcp:120697:72"/> thee all neceſſaries. It is fit thou ſhouldſt lay hold upon the divine providence, oppoſing it to thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent affliction; and that thou mayeſt prevent the feare of future evill, drive away ſorrow, and ſay unto thy ſoule, why art thou heavy, O my ſoule, and why art thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.6. Behold, the great God who hath hitherto loaden me with ſo many benefits, and is not as yet weary to doe me good, hee promiſeth to helpe me for the future, and to bee loving and carefull of mee, ſo that hee will never forſake mee. That thou mayeſt taſte the goodneſſe of the moſt high, and perceive how ſweet the Lord is, and firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is carefull of thee in thy preſent affliction, thou muſt lay this in the firſt place as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, That God is thy heavenly father, not onely for that he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and brought thee into this
<pb facs="tcp:120697:73"/> world, but chiefely for the benefit of redemption purchaſed unto thee through his ſonne Jeſus Chriſt, with whom thou art joyned by faith; ſo as thou art one with him, and a member of his body, and conſequently one of thoſe to whom he gave power to become the ſonnes of God, even thoſe that believe in his name, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. and are borne of God, wherefore hee will not bee aſhamed to call them brethren, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore thou art one of the number of Gods children, God being thy father, thou wilt not doubt that hee is not fatherly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted towards thee, and that hee will not nouriſh, cheriſh, cloath, conſerve, deliver; and bee preſent with thee in all places, unleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance thou art fallen into wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe even ſo farre, as to believe God to be a degenerate father, and deſtitute of fatherly affection, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:73"/> ſo more baſe and worſer than earthly fathers. God forbid, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as he is more infinitly perfect than thoſe, ſo for goodneſſe and bountifulneſſe towards his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren hee infinitly ſurpaſſeth them. Our Saviour tearmes our earthly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers evill, for that ſometimes they forſake their children, make them miſchievous, and bring them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: but there is not this, nor any ſuch vitioſity in God, he being goodneſſe, mercy, and love it ſelfe; ſo that howſoever a woman may forget her ſucking infant, yet God cannot his children, whom he hath graven upon the palmes of his hands. The greatneſſe of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall affection is herein evident, that hee ſo loved the world, the world, I ſay, which had ſo many manner of wayes offended him, that hee gave his onely begotten ſonne, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. He that ſpared not his owne ſonne, but delivered
<pb facs="tcp:120697:74"/> him up for us all, how ſhall hee not give us all things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. Moreover, hee is not onely a father of that goodneſſe, whereby wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly he hath care of thee, but his will is conjoyned with power; ſo that hee can provide neceſſaries for his children. Neither may hee bee reſembled to thoſe earthly fathers, who oftentimes verily are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willing to ſuccour the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and miſery of their children, but being deſtitute of meanes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring their will to effect, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon oftentimes a moſt loving fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is conſtrained to behold his child expiring and periſhing, but cannot help him; or being certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the miſery of his child, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving elſewhere from him, cannot ſuccour him; or which is more, he is oftentimes ignorant of the ſtate of his child, he is ſo farre off from relieving him. The caſe is farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with our heavenly father,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:74"/> for hee is God, and therefore moſt wiſe, who is acquainted with all our necſſities, takes notice of all our baniſhments, and puts our tears into his bottles; your heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knoweth that yee have need of all theſe things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.8. If the devill and world imagine any thing againſt thee, he knows long before their machinations; for he penetrateth the deepeſt thoughts. Hee is acquainted with ſuch meanes as tend to thy comfort, conſervation, and deliverance; hee overſeeth and ordaines things, or ever they exiſt; hee can extract good from evill, and of darkneſſe create light; he is omnipotent, for by the word of the Lord were the heavens made, and all the hoaſt of them by the breath of his mouth: for he ſpeaks, and whatſoever is, is done, hee commandeth, and it ſtands faſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6.9. he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth and ordereth all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:75"/> inſomuch that they cannot move without his permiſſion and will. The ſea, earth, and all that therein is depend upon his beck; he healeth the broken in heart, and bindeth up their wounds; hee tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the number of the ſtarres, and calleth them all by their names. Great is our Lord, and of great power, his underſtanding is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. The Lord lifteth up the meek, hee caſteth the wicked downe to the ground. Sing unto the Lord with thankſgiving, ſing praiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Harpe unto our God, who covereth the heavens with clouds, who prepareth raine for the earth: hee ſendeth forth his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the earth, his word runneth very ſwiftly, hee giveth ſnow like wooll, hee ſcattereth his hoare froſt like aſhes, hee caſteth forth his ice like morſels, who can ſtand before his cold? hee ſendeth forth his word and melteth them,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:75"/> he cauſeth the wind to blow, and the waters flow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.3,4,5,6,7,8,15,16,17,18. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing thou haſt ſuch a gracious powerfull father, wilt thou doubt he will not bee carefull of thee, and will not, and cannot, further thy imployments? In the ſecond place, I would have thee conſider what great care hee took of thee hitherto, how he hath till this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent houre governed thee by his providence; nouriſhed, cheriſhed, conſerved, preſerved thee from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable evills, and rid thee out of a great many dangers and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; how often, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner of wayes haſt thou had experience of his benevolence, as we have declared, eſpecially in the preceding chapter? ſay then to thy ſelfe, hee that hitherto hath beene carefull of me, yea, before I came into this world, even hee will care for me for the future; and as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
<pb facs="tcp:120697:76"/> hee hath not forſaken mee, ſo hereafter hee will not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto mee. I would have thee conſider further, what manifold benefits hee hath beſtowed upon thee even before thy converſion, when thou wert under the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſinne, a ſworne enemy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and child of wrath; ſo that thou couldſt hope for no other than puniſhment inſtead of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and curſes inſtead of bleſſings; yet notwithſtanding he hath really teſtified unto thee, how gracious his goodneſſe is, and that hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſun to riſe on the evill, and on the good, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.45. How much more carefull will hee be of thee in providing thee all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſince thou art received into his grace, and made partaker of that honour, whereby thou art one of the number of his ſonnes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a brother and friend of Jeſus Chriſt? and ſince thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt
<pb facs="tcp:120697:76"/> in his feare, and indevoureſt in thine infirmities to be conformable to his will, hating thy ſins, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting thy ſelfe to his ſervice. And verily. Gods children are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tried in their adverſities, ſtrengthning themſelves in the hope of future things by ſuch things as are paſt, whereof the kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> affords us a notable example, to wit, in the 27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> for conſidering with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in times paſt, how that God had delivered him from the hands of all his enemies, he is confident, and fully perſwades himſelfe, that God will continue for the future, and always, his favour and ſuccour towards him; When the wicked, even mine enemies, and my foes, came upon me to eat up my fleſh, they ſtumbled and fell; Though an hoaſt of men were laid againſt me, yet I will put my truſt in him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.3. But if thou ſhouldſt
<pb facs="tcp:120697:77"/> indure ſome unheard-of miſeries, which experience could not para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell, thou ſhouldſt then have ſome reaſon of doubting and diffidence, in that which concernes thee, but ſince thy owne experience can prove this to be otherwiſe, thou ſhouldſt in no wiſe doubt of his divine providence for the future, and of his fatherly care of thee for the preſent. But what doe I mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie words touching his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which is cleerly ſeene in thy behalfe? the great husbandman ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth his care even to the leaſt creatures to their profit, good, and conſervation, and provideth them all neceſſaries; hee giveth fodder unto the cattell, and feedeth the young ravens that call upon him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.9. O Lord, thou ſaveſt man and beaſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.7. all theſe wait upon thee, that thou mayeſt give them meat in due ſeaſon. Thou giveſt it them, they gather it,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:77"/> and when thou openeſt thy hand, they are filled with good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.27.28. How much more carefull will hee be of thee? Thus the Lord himſelfe teacheth us to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; behold the foules of the aire, for they ſow not, neither doe they reap, nor gather into barnes, yet your heavenly father feedeth them; Are ye not much better than they? Conſider the lilies of the field, how they grow, they toil not, nor doe they ſpinne; And yet I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his glory was not arrayed like one of theſe; wherefore if God ſo cloath the graſſe of the field, which to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the oven, ſhall hee not much more cloath you, O yee of little faith? <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.26,28,29,30. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, are not two ſparrowes ſold for a fathing, and one of them ſhall not fall to the ground without your father? but the very haires
<pb facs="tcp:120697:78"/> of your head are all numbred, feare yee not therefore, yee are of more value than many ſparrowes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29,30,31. Thou canſt in no wiſe doubt then of his gracious providence, unleſſe perhaps thou art fallen into wickednes and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, as to think God to be more unjuſt, worſer, and more unwiſe, than earthly fathers, who verily take care of their cattell, much more of their children. Hither may be referred the promiſes of Gods fatherly care towards his children, whom hee alwayes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth, and never purpoſeth to withdraw his helping hand from them: ſo that hee enjoynes the faithfull man wholly to rely upon his providence. Commit thy way unto the Lord, truſt alſo in him, and hee ſhall bring it to paſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. call upon me in the day of trouble, I will deliver thee, &amp; thou ſhalt glorifie mee, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.15.
<pb facs="tcp:120697:78"/> becauſe hee hath ſet his heart upon me, and I will anſwer him, and I will bee with him in trouble; I will deliver him, and with length of dayes will I ſatisfie him, and ſhew him my ſalvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.14,15,16. be conrent with ſuch things as yee have, for hee ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that not onely benefits and proſperity happen, according to Gods providence, to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but miſeries and adverſities proceed from the ſame fountaine. Now ſince God continually wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth over his children, his eyes being with ſingular care fixt upon them; it is certain, that adverſities cannot eſcape the ſight (as I may ſo ſay) of his wildome, but are laid upon the godly, according to his will and providence and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they happen unto us, according to the will of our heavenly father,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:79"/> it cannot be but that he layeth them upon us to our good and profit, and the rather for that they proceed from his love towards us; ſo that not to relie upon Gods providence is incredulity, diſobedience, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his wiſdome, goodneſſe, juſtice, truth, and providence, it is ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude towards him, contempt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting of his divine honour, and in effect not to account him for thy father, nor thy ſelfe for his ſonne. But thou wilt ſay, it is true, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge God hath ſingular care of his godly children; but as for me I have too grievouſly offended, and provoked him to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by my ſins, and therefore farre be it from me, to think I have cauſe to confide in his providence; nay, cleane contrary, I have reaſon to expect rather his wrath, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and horrible judgement: Whereunto I anſwer, that God notwithſtanding thy demerits is
<pb facs="tcp:120697:79"/> thy heavenly father, not as thou art in thy ſelfe, but as thou art his adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſonne in Chriſt Jeſus, who hath done thee good in this life, and in that which is to come. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> bleſſed not <hi>Jacob</hi> in his owne perſon, but in his elder brothers, in whoſe garments he was inveſted, and whoſe name he borrowed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his owne. Bee moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured then of Gods love notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thy iniquities, whereby thou draweſt upon thy ſelfe his chaſtiſements, but to thy profit and ſalvation. And herein hee reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth a father that deveſteth not himſelfe of his fatherly affection, neither ceaſeth to benefit his child, though hee be angry with him; and chaſtiſeth him in regard of his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe and lewdneſſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing thou art reconciled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, thou mayeſt not repreſent him to thy ſelfe, as a judge puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the guilty, but as a father
<pb facs="tcp:120697:80"/> chaſtiſing his ſonne, thereby teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying what great care hee hath of him, and how dearely hee loves him; for by correcting him hee prevents his ruine and deſtruction. And the anſwer is eaſie, to what thou ſayeſt further, if the Lord loves me why doth hee viſit mee with this or that affliction? and with <hi>Gideon,</hi> who being as yet well catechiſed, ſaid unto the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> heare O my Lord, if the Lord be with us, why is all this befallen us? <hi>Jud.</hi> 6.13. which is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine language of a ſonne feeling the rod, and thereupon concludes that his father ſets aſide his nature and affection towards him, which is all one as if one ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of his father for giving him bread, which is ſo neceſſary for him; or if a patient ſhould taxe the Phiſitian of inhumanity and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, for miniſtring him a potion: hee that deemeth that God loves
<pb facs="tcp:120697:80"/> him not, and that his fatherly care is alienated, becauſe hee chaſtiſeth him, doth no otherwiſe than if he ſhould ſay, God loves me not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee does mee good: for chaſtiſement wherewith his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are exerciſed is a moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neceſſary benefit during the nonage of their life: but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the following chapter, It now being ſufficient to declare, that hee will alwayes take care of thee, ſeeing thou art his ſonne, in the whole courſe of thy life, by his providence and meet help hee will bee really carefull of thee ſo farre, that thou mayeſt poſſeſſe thy mind in tranquillity, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and time to come. Certainly, if thy ſtate and condition did not depend upon the providence of thy good and beſt father, but blind fortune as Atheiſts deeme, verily thou ſhouldſt have alwayes juſt cauſe of ſorrow, terrour, diſquiet,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:81"/> feare, and anguiſh: But now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is nothing befals thee, but according to Gods will and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, thou mayeſt ſay by right with and to thy ſelfe, Returne O my ſoule into thy reſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7. And hence it is manifeſt how much happier thou art than the Ethnicks, and other infidels who are altogether ignorant of Gods providence, or know it not to be of that nature, as thou art taught by his word: And therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee, but theſe wretches ſhould be expoſed to horrible perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mind among ſo many tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſes and troubles of this life. But thou that art brought up in Gods ſchoole, and art not ignorant, that all things are ruled and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the providence of God thy heavenly father, mayeſt enjoy a quiet calme mind no otherwiſe than the heaven, which is cleer and ſerene, though the ayre be covered
<pb facs="tcp:120697:81"/> with thick clouds, and toſſed up and downe with wind and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; ſo that by right thou mayeſt crie with the beſt of the fathers, O thou omnipotent good, who careſt for every one of us ſo, as if thou didſt onely for us and of us all, as of each of us in particular, <hi>Aug. confeſs. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. Away then with all ſorrow, ſince God will be carefull of thee for the future; and as for the preſent adverſity that thou feeleſt, it hath no other origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, than the beſt and wiſeſt will of thy heavenly father, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes aymeth at thy good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Further, ſeeing hee is indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigably carefull of thee, ſubmit thy ſelfe altogether to his will and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence with an holy and filial o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in thy preſent and future condition; Imitate Jeſus Chriſt, who ſaid, O my father, not as I will but as thou wilt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39, follow his guidance without
<pb facs="tcp:120697:82"/> tergiverſation, and with <hi>David</hi> be ready at all points to performe the commands of thy heavenly King. Bee prepared for all things, and compoſe thy ſelfe to undergoe any condition, whether proſperous, or miſerable, being aſſured that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever befals thee tendeth to thy profit. Humble thy ſelfe under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt thee in due time; caſt all thy care upon him, for hee careth for thee, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6,7. and why ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou aſide, withdrawing thy lelfe from receiving his counſell and will, ſeeing hee worketh all things according to the counſell of his owne will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. and the counſell of the Lord ſtandeth for ever, the thoughts of his heart to all generations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. ſo that all things happen ſo as he hath decreed. Thy reſiſtance then, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of heart, impatience, will ſtand thee in no ſtead, neither will
<pb facs="tcp:120697:82"/> hinder what is decreed to come to paſſe. Conſider the worke of the Lord, for who can make that ſtraight which he hath crooked? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.11. ſeeing then that God takes care of thee, away with that carefulneſſe, which ſo tormenteth the children of this world. I ſpeak not of the lawfull care of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of our publique and private vocation, neither of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, wiſdome, induſtry, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the uſe of ſuch means as are ordained of God; but I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that carefulneſſe which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from diffidence towards Gods providence, and incredulity towards his promiſes, from the love of this world, covetouſneſſe, ambition; I underſtand that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, which as it proceeds from this Originall, ſo it hath for its concomitants an ambitious mind, ſorrow even appearing in its rough attire, illiberality towards
<pb facs="tcp:120697:83"/> the neighbour, which drawes after it at laſt not onely unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but all manner of calamities, and oftentime deſperation it ſelfe. As for thee, do thy duty as becomes a wiſe man endued with vertue, fearing God; Commit the events of future, and ſuch things as are not within thy power to God. And herein imitate <hi>Joab,</hi> who ſaid to his brother, bee of good courage, and let us play the men, for out people, and for the city of our God, the Lord doe that ſeemeth him good, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.12. Now ſince hee takes care of thee, and all thy actions, certainly thou wouldſt moſt grievouſly injure him, if thou ſhouldſt thruſt in thy ſickle, as they uſe to ſpeak, and reap his harveſt. Or perchance thou thinkeſt that God can have no conſideration of thy affaires, ſince thou art a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble terreſtriall worme, God I ſay, who governeth the heavens, ſea,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:83"/> and all that therein is. How foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh would that traveller bee dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which would vexe and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment himſelf, where to go on in his way, even then when directed by a faithfull skilfull guide? How grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therefore is thy fooliſhneſſe by being thy owne executioner, through anxietie, and carefulneſſe, ſince he is now preſent with thee, who takes care of thee? Gracious children commit themſelves to the care of their parents, but a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and wicked ſonne muſt order himſelfe, and things; whereupon he caſts him headlong into moſt grievous errours, and extreme mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. Further, if God be carefull of thee, away with all feare, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that of God, away with all puſillanimity; for ſince hee takes care of thee, who conteineth all things in his powerfull hand, and bendeth all the Creatures to his beck, why art thou afraid of them?
<pb facs="tcp:120697:84"/> doe not feare Sathan, for hee hath not power even over ſwine, what can he have over Gods child? Be like afraid of men, who though they are powerfull and cruell, yet their breath is in their noſthrills, and they are nought but tailes of ſmoaking firebrands, <hi>Eſay</hi> 7.4. The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, as the rivers of waters, he turneth it whether ſoever hee will, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1. He turnes their minds contrary to their nature, to favour Gods children, as hee gave his people favour in the ſight of the Egyptians, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.21. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he looſe the bridle to their perverſe will againſt his children, yet hee blindeth and deprives them of underſtanding, inſomuch that they know not what to doe, and, or attend not what is to bee done. But if perchance they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to goe about ſome ill counſell, hee takes away their power or
<pb facs="tcp:120697:84"/> courage that they cannot bring it to paſſe, or if they have meanes and will to put the ſame in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he makes their indeavours of none effect, ſcattereth their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, and reduceth by his power their devices to nothing; for hee bringeth the counſell of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to nought, and maketh the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the people of none effect, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.10. Inſomuch that thou mayeſt confidently ſay, The Lord is my helper, and I will not feare what man ſhall doe unto me, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.6. The laſt and worſt enemy is death; but why ſhouldſt thou be afraid thereof, being the end and period of all evills, and an entrance into bleſſedneſſe? Therfore though I walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, for thou art with me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. Laſtly, ſince God by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence takes care of thee, be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, and of firme hope for the
<pb facs="tcp:120697:85"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſhould ſo much the more fill thy mind, by how much thou haſt hitherto had experience, and taſted how ſweet the Lord is. Let the time paſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e unto thee an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the time to come, let the experience of thoſe benefits which thou haſt hitherto received, bring forth in thee hope that maketh not aſhamed, when grounded and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in God. And take heed, thou ſayeſt, I ſee not how ſuch or ſuch a thing may be brought to paſſe, there being no apparent meanes; for God knoweth perfectly the means, and can work even without means, yea, above meanes, and againſt all appearance thereof. Let his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſuffice thee. The tribe of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> caſhiered hope of poſſeſſing the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that becauſe of their owne weakneſſe and want of power, and the might and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their enemies, whereof they were not ignorant; the hill is not
<pb facs="tcp:120697:85"/> enough for us, ſay they, and all the <hi>Canaanites</hi> that dwell in the land of the valley have Chariots of iron. Heare <hi>Ioſhuah's</hi> anſwer, The moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſhall bee thine, thou ſhalt drive out the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> though they have iron chariots, and though they be ſtrong, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 17.18. The reaſon is grounded upon Gods promiſe, whoſe word is more powerfull than all things: wait for the Lord, and thou ſhalt ſee his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand; ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, which hee ſhall ſhew to thee to day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. Where to ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, are joyned together; Why art thou therefore caſt downe, O my ſoule, and why art thou diſquieted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me? Hope in God, for I will yet praiſe him, who is the helpe of my countenance, and my God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:120697:86"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. The ſixth ground or reaſon is, that afflictions themſelves yield matter of joy.</head>
               <p>BUt what doe I ſay? not onely the benefits, but the evils of this life commonly ſo called, that is to ſay, adverſities which thou endureſt as long as thou dwelleſt in theſe tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> yield mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of joy, which is a riddle, which the Philiſtines of this world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſolve. The <hi>Nazarites</hi> and children of God are onely ſenſible, that there is hony in the Lion, and ſweetneſſe in affliction. This leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is very neceſſary to every one, and in it ſelfe moſt excellent; for thereby wee are taught to look
<pb facs="tcp:120697:86"/> upon afflictions undauntedly, and entertaine them not onely with contempt, as the Philoſophers teach, but with a merry counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with pleaſure and gladneſſe, which without compariſon is farre more laudable and excellent than ſtoicall contempt, and prond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, which cannot long endure the brunt of greater evils, but will in ſhort ſpace be foiled, and put to flight with ſhame. Now mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is not capable of this doctrine, unleſſe it hath firſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the goodneſſe lying hid under the deformed vizard of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, which con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſts herein, that the affictions which God layeth upon his elect, are the meanes whereby they obtaine the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of eternall happineſſe, and thoſe unſpeakable good things which are prepared for them; ſo that their end is moſt excellent, of ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value, even heavenly life, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:87"/> glory, which neither eye ſaw, nor eare heard, nor the heart of man can conceive. That thou mayeſt perfectly underſtand this doctrine, it is neceſſary that thou conſider the divers ſorts of afflictions, which God ſendeth to his children, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of commonly they make two; one ſort is of thoſe afflictions which are common to the godly, with the children of this world, as diſeaſes, poverty, or the like: The other ſort is of thoſe afflictions that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per unto ſuch as undergo the croſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, or perſecution, where with the faithfull, for the profeſſion of the Goſpell, are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted by their enemies: but to ſpeak properly, if we look upon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, as they out wardly appeare unto us, there is not any affliction proper, all are common; but if we conſider their intrinſecall forme, which gives them their being and eſſence, there is not any common,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:87"/> but all are particular and proper: for their extrinſecall forme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in that which is grievous, and carries with it anguiſh of heart, as poverty (as hath beene ſaid) diſeaſes, baniſhment, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, all which are common to the godly with the children of this world, inſomuch that there is not any affliction which may not as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually befall them both; for what have we not common, ſaith one of the Fathers, as long as we are in this world, with the children ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and as long as wee are here below, wee are joyned with other men by the bonds of this corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fleſh, but in ſpirit we are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from them; ſo that till this corruptible ſhall bee clothed with incorruption, and this mortall ſhall put on immortality, &amp; we aſcend to God the father, all the diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of the fleſh are common to us with them. If the earth be barren,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:88"/> famine makes no diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween any; if a City or Town be ſurpriſed by the enemy, all are brought into captivity; and when the clouds with-hold their raine, all are compelled to endure this drought; and when the rocks ſplit the ſhip aſunder, all without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion endure the ſame wrack; fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of eyes, burning agues, and the perfect health of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are common to us with them, as long as we are clothed with the ſame common fleſh in this world. As touching that which gives eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to the afflictions of Gods children, it is opinion according to Philoſophy: But Gods word cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects this opinion, teaching us that it cannot give, unleſſe an imaginary and putative eſſence thereunto. Their true eſſence then is that which God himſelfe gives them, who wills that ſome ſerve for to chaſtiſe his elect, correct their
<pb facs="tcp:120697:88"/> vices, ſome ſerve for to trie their faith and other vertues, and others tend to this end, that they may beare witneſſe to his heavenly truth. Now as there is not any affliction of Gods children, but hath reference to one of theſe, ſo they are of that nature, that they never befall the wicked, ſince hee is not their father; neither trieth hee them in that whereof they are deſtitute, neither honoureth them ſo faire, as to make them witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his truth, which they are ignorant of, or cannot away with. To ſpeak properly then, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man hath not any affliction common with the unregenerate, if wee reſpect as wee ought its true being; neither any particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, if we conſider its outward forme and ſpecies. And this wee muſt obſerve by reaſon of the fruit and conſolation, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound thereby to God's children,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:89"/> as ſhall bee ſeen hereafter. There are three ſorts of afflictions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God exerciſeth his children, chaſtiſement, triall, and Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: of all and each of which we ſay, that they procure to the godly ineſtimable good things, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eſpecially, and eternall life. That the verity hereof may the better be perceived, let us firſt, as to what concerne chaſtiſement, compare proſperity and adverſity. Who knoweth not, that whereas proſperity ſhould be a ſpurre to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and haſten us with more ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity to the marke of our high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to render thankes unto God in ſuch ſort as is meet, that is, to worſhip and love him with more affection, and to glorifie him in all our thoughts, words, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; who knoweth not, I ſay, what it doth inſtead of all this. It corrupteth us, the blame is ours, and brings forth ſuch effects as it
<pb facs="tcp:120697:89"/> ought not to produce. It is true, the godly man offends God in his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity through murmurings, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and other ſinnes; but hee recollects and returnes unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, aſſoone as with <hi>David</hi> hee entreth the ſanctuary: but this is little or nothing to that he doth in the time of proſperity; for if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity hath kill'd her thouſand, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly proſperity hath kill'd her ten thouſand. It is proſperity that breedeth carnall ſecurity, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of God, confidence in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affaires, pride, prophanation, love to this world, contempt of Gods word and ſacraments. It ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focates godly zeale, and extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth fervency of prayers; it bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth and hideth the fire of faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the aſhes of carnall concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, and affections. In a word, the ſummer of proſperity engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth a numerous ſwarme of flies, that is to ſay, vices which waſte,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:90"/> and make deſolate the garden of the Lord: This point needs no proofe, the Scripture being plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full herein, and every mans expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience witneſſing it to be the way to eternall condemnation, and not to life; wherfore that God may bring into the right way one that is as a miſerable wandring ſheep, hee takes him his paſtorall ſtaffe, not ſmiting him on this ſide, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while on that ſide. He eſpecially ſends upon him ſuch chaſtiſements as are correſpondent to his faults and crimes, that ſo he may earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be moved, returne to himſelfe, and amend his life; for if he hath been unmercifull, and hard hearted to his neighbour, God ſo diſpoſeth it, that hee ſhall alſo feele iron hearts which will not be moved with compaſſion towards him; who ſo ſtoppeth his eare at the cry of the poore, he ſhall cry himſelfe, and ſhall not be heard, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.13.
<pb facs="tcp:120697:90"/> and God ſaith by the Prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> yee have not hearkened unto me, in proclaming liberty every one to his neighbour; behold, I proclame a liberty for you to the ſword, to the peſtilence, to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>Jer.</hi> 34.17. or if hee hath committed adultery, murder, he is oftentimes puniſhed after the ſame manner, either in his owne perſon, or in ſuch as belong unto him; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe herein King <hi>David;</hi> if for the feare of men hee is aſhamed of Chriſt Jeſus, and forſaketh the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpell to addict himſelfe to Idolatry, God will ſend his puniſhment upon him in this world, for ye ſhall be aſhamed of the oakes which yee have deſired, and ye ſhall be confounded for the gardens that ye have choſen; for ye ſhall be as an oake whoſe leafe fadeth, and as a garden that hath no water, <hi>Eſay,</hi> 9.29,30. Briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if hee hath walked perverſely
<pb facs="tcp:120697:91"/> with God, and as the Scripture ſpeaks, followed his owne wayes, God knowes how to recompence him in like manner. If yee walke contrary unto me, ſaith God, then I will walke contrary unto you alſo in fury, and I even I will chaſtiſe you ſeven times for your ſinnes, <hi>Levit,</hi> 29.30. and againe, they have choſen their owne wayes, and their ſoule delighted in their abominations: I will alſo chuſe their deluſions, and bring their feares upon them, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 66.34. not that God hath pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turne from his way and live, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.11. for wee are chaſtened of the Lord, that wee ſhould not be condemned with the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. When God therefore chaſtiſeth his elect, they reap profit thereby; for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto themſelves, bethinke what they have hitherto done,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:91"/> heartily deteſting their evill deeds, no otherwiſe than <hi>Joſeph's</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whom when they could not perſwade, being as yet unknowne unto them, with intreaties, wee are verily guilty, ſay they, concerning our brother, in that wee ſaw the anguiſh of his ſoule, when hee beſought us, and we would not heare; therefore is this diſtreſſe come upon us, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.21. They ſue unto God for the pardon of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſinnes, they flie unto his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, renounce ſinne for the future, keep themſelves warily from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againe into the like ſins; they ſhake off ſpirituall drowſineſſe, bid adien to pride, renounce the love of this world, and daily ſtrive more and more to deveſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of that coat of skinne, I meane ſinne, which <hi>Adam</hi> left them as a legacy. In the time of adverſity, the lampe of faith is kindled, and ſhines with brighter
<pb facs="tcp:120697:92"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120697:92"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120697:93"/> rayes, and ſhooteth them further; as alſo truſt in God which raiſeth the dead, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. Then doth patience and hope increaſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tribulation worketh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and patience experience, experience hope, that maketh not aſhamed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3,4. thence proceed fervent prayers, ſerious loathing of this world, and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for eternall life; ſo that the faithfull crieth out with <hi>David,</hi> my ſoule crieth out for the living God, when ſhall I come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God? <hi>Pſah.</hi> 42.3. Hence alſo it followeth, that the afflictions of this nature are ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that none can bee ſaved without them; God's children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like good corne, which is not put in the garner ere it be thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Man's heart is naturally ſo ſtony, that it cannot be fitted to make up the eternall temple of our heavenly <hi>Solomon,</hi> unleſſe it bee
<pb facs="tcp:120697:93"/> hewed and poliſhed with the ſtroakes of afflictions, which I confeſſe are irkeſome to fleſh and bloud, yet exceeding neceſſary thereunto; no otherwiſe than the Sunne and fire, which is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us, though ſometimes intollerable: wee conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as to what eſpecially concerns chaſtiſements, and ſay that they containe in them ineſtimable good things, fince they are ſingular and very neceſſary meanes to the attainment of eternall happineſſe. If the ends of chaſtiſements be ſo glorious and happy, much more the end of trials which are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent onely to ſuch as are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto God by chaſtiſements, preaching of the word, and the efficacy of the Holy Ghoſt, doe live diligently in the feare of God, and are heedfull as farre forth as the imperſection of grace in this life gives them ſcope not to offend
<pb facs="tcp:120697:94"/> him. They are called trials, not that God by them would be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the faith and ſincerity of his children, which hee moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knowes; neither chiefely thereby, becauſe hee would make knowne unto them their owne weakneſſe or infirmities, which they themſelves know to bee in the higheſt degree; but they are ſo called, becauſe ſuch a thing happens therein, as falls out, when one trieth or maketh proofe of the ability or ſtrength of another; for hee not onely that makes proofe, but he that is tried and ſet upon la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth with might and maine, that hee bee not foiled or vanquiſhed. The caſe is no otherwiſe in theſe trials, which God layeth upon his children, which live in his feare, and conforme themſelves to his holy will: for God on his part makes a vehement aſſault upon them by, ſome notable calamity,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:94"/> but they on the other ſide by the efficacy of the Holy Ghoſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in them reſiſt valiantly through faith, patience, perſeverance, till they obtaine the victory; ſo that they will not yeeld unto tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor commit any ſinne, or wickedneſſe, wherein <hi>Satan,</hi> the world, and the fleſh, ſhall ſtrive to entangle them by meanes of that affliction, and that for the moſt part under this pretence, that there is no way for them to eſcape, and to be rid thereof, but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting this or that heinous ſinne. In adverſity all the Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues doe moſt wonderfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and without compariſon more clearly appeare, than in the time of proſperity, not unlike the ſtarres which are not viſible at noon day, yet appeare in the night time with wonderfull rayes, or <hi>Gideons</hi> fire-brands, which were in his ſouldiers pitchers, not appearing,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:95"/> or giving any light til their pitchers were broken. Then other faithfull men are edified, and God glorified, inſomuch, that afflictions reſemble that precious ointment powred upon Chriſts head, which filled the houſe with its odour: but all this comes wholly from Gods grace, whoſe ſtrength is perfected in weakneſſe, ſo that the faithfull may ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> when I am weak then am I ſtrong, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. ſalvation and everlaſting glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of neceſſity followeth this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict and victory: for the triall of your faith, ſaith Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> being much more precious than gold that periſheth, though it be tried by fire, might be found unto praiſe, glory and honour, at the appearing of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. as wee find a notable example, to wit, <hi>Job,</hi> worthy our obſervation, of all theſe afflictions; ſo wee have a lively repreſentation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:120697:95"/> mans triall in the wraſtling of <hi>Jacob</hi> the patriarch, who after hee had valiantly ſtrove all night, and obtained the victory, and his ſoule delivered, I have ſeen God, ſaith hee, face to face, and my life is preſerved, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.20. O moſt wonderfull combat, where the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailant and defendant is the very ſame, where the conquerour and the party conquered is the very ſame; and where the conquerour gives the glory to the party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querd, which is alſo given to the conquerour; where the party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered is as a King, ruling and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, and the conquerour is as an humble ſervant obeying him. The third and laſt ſort of the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the godly is martyrdome, which comprehendeth all ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions as the faithfull man ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and ſuſtaineth, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant profeſſion of celeſtiall truth, as baniſhment, impriſonment,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:96"/> ſtripes, torments, loſſe of goods, and eſpecially death it ſelfe. And this ſort of afflictions containes in it more good things and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities than the former; for beſides the joyfull end that it hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with chaſtiſements, and trials, by the promiſe of Chriſt, who ſaith, bleſſed are they which are perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for righteouſneſſe ſake; for theirs is the Kingdome of heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.10. Beſides this, I ſay, God honoureth the faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his truth with more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, in that hee promiſeth them above others a greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of reward in his heavenly kingdome; and therefore he ſaith, not onely ſuch as endure perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have a reward in heaven, but he addeth alſo this, Great is your reward in heaven, whereby he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies ſome ſingular glory which the Martyrs enjoy in heaven. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is to be referred,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:96"/> our light which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, worketh for us farre more exceeding and eternall weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. for albeit this ſentence may bee applied to the two former ſorts of afflictions, which procure alſo eternall life; yet the Apoſtle, here eſpecially, ſpeaks of thoſe afflictions, which he and the reſt of his faithfull aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciats ſuffered for the word of truth. Moreover, theſe ſufferings have Gods notable promiſe of the benefits of this life alſo. Verily I ſay unto you, ſaith Chriſt, there is no man that hath left houſe, or bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or ſiſters, or father, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or wife, or children, or lands, for my ſake, and the Goſpells, but hee ſhall receive a hundred told, now in this time, houſes, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſiſters, and mothers, and children, and lands with perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the world to come e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.29,30. This
<pb facs="tcp:120697:97"/> promiſe in ſome of the faithfull is literally fulfilled. God oftentimes beſtowing upon them farre more good things, honours, and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, than they were deprived of, for the acknowledgement of his truth, whereas in others it takes effect by equivalence; for it is moſt manifeſt, that all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles thereof are not literally to be fulfilled; As for example ſake, if one inſtead of his father, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or ſonne, ſhould obtain thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand fathers, mothers, &amp;c. they reap then the fruit and verity of this promiſe, when they receive things of equivalent or better va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue to the things promiſed, and that with perſecution; that is to ſay, though they want, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of theſe earthly commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which happens, when the faithfull man is moſt aſſured of his adoption, and conſequently of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inheritance, which is farre
<pb facs="tcp:120697:97"/> more excellent and better than all riches and rewards, and indeed is the onely reward worthy to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of God, and received of the faithfull. Hence it is that he is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to know, that all the riches of the world are his by the right of adoption, as being the child of God, and deſigned to Lord it over all the creatures, howſoever they be conferred upon him according to meane and meaſure, even as his tutour and phyſician; yea, his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father knowes it to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and conducible. Hee is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured alſo of Gods providence, and moſt fully perſwaded in himſelfe, that hee hath therein an unexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted fountaine, and oile that will never faile; for hee believes his word to be moſt true: ſeek ye firſt the Kingdome of heaven, and his righteouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. He that ſpareth not his owne
<pb facs="tcp:120697:98"/> ſonne, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall hee not with him freely give us all things? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. Such joy attends this certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſalvation in him, as ſurpaſſeth all the riches of this world; for godlineſſe with contentment is great gaine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6. which vertuous contentment gives clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and brighter luſtre, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it with its contrary in them, which willingly would ſuffer not any thing for Gods truth, but turne their backs thereunto, renouncing Chriſt; for in the midſt of their abundance of the goods and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this world, by the juſt judgement of God, they are not contented with their owne condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but are toſſed with moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous perturbations, by reaſon of the torments of their conſcience, which will ſooner, or later awake. Adde hereunto this benefit, to wit, the honour which God imparteth
<pb facs="tcp:120697:98"/> unto ſuch as have conſtantly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for his heavenly truth; for what great honour is it, I beſeech thee, that the King of Kings vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes to call a miſerable terreſtriall worme to be a witneſſe againſt his enemies, that accuſe him of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, to plead his cauſe and defend his honour? what great honour is it to be received and enrolled into the Colledge and ſociety of the Prophets, Apoſtles, and that grand cloud of Martyrs that have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for his heavenly truth? yea, what great honour is it to be a companion of Jeſus Chriſt, the Prince of our ſalvation, who was conſecrated through afflictions, to be cloathed with the ſame ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and weare the crowne of thornes with him, and ſo to bee conformable unto him, and alwayes to beare about in the body the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord Jeſus, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb facs="tcp:120697:99"/> in our body, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10. What great honour doth Chriſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe us alſo, in taking our afflictions to be his, when as he ſaith, that our perſecutions and ſufferings are the reſidues and reliques of his afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and markes? what honour is it to be choſen of God, as a great Emperour, or warlike Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to beſiege with a ſtrong Army a certaine City; for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hee electeth not daſtards or cowards, but moſt generous and valiant men: ſo that theſe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are publique teſtimonies of our valiancy, and royall charters, whereof wee may glory with the Apoſtle, who ſaith, moſt gladly will I glory in my infirmities, that the power of God may reſt upon me? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. what great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is it to fight in the ſight of the King of Kings, who is preſident and overſeer of the combat, and diſtributes crownes? what great
<pb facs="tcp:120697:99"/> honour is it to be ſuch a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtrument as God uſeth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his Church, the bloud and afflictions of the Martyrs being the ſeed of the Church, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perſecutions would never have been ſo much amplified, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Againe, what honour is it to be Gods inſtrument, to caſt down and overthrow all infernall and worldly powers, to deſtroy prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers that rebell againſt him? And I beſeech thee, knoweſt thou not what is the cauſe of the ruine of Empires, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Common-wealths? it is becauſe they make inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Gods children, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, otherwiſe they might have ſubſiſted longer: for <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> is a cup of trembling unto the people round about, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.2. The Church is like unto mount Sinah, whereunto if a man or beaſt drawes neere is thruſt through, and
<pb facs="tcp:120697:100"/> killed with darts from heaven, or an anvill whereupon all the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers that ſtrike or beat are broken into ſhivers; ſo that the enemies of Gods truth cannot commit a greater meaſure of fooliſhneſſe, and prove more prejudiciall unto themſelves, then when they fight againſt Gods Church: they undoe themſelves thereby, turning upſide downe their thrones, loſing their Crownes, and caſting headlong their children and poſterity into a miſerable condition. And thus much of the ineſtimable good things of the third ſort of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Seeing theſe things are ſo, who ſeeth not, that all the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mentioned, are not ſignes of Gods wrath and indignation, but of his love, foraſmuch as they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch a glorious end. And thus the Holy Ghoſt himſelfe giveth his verdict of chaſtiſements in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; whom the Lord loveth hee
<pb facs="tcp:120697:100"/> chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth every ſonne whom he receiveth. If yee endure chaſtening, God dealeth with you as with ſonnes; for what ſonne is he whom the father cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth not? and if ye be without chaſtiſements, whereof all are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, then are you baſtards, not ſonnes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6,7,8. Now if chaſtiſements and puniſhments inflicted for ſinnes, are not ſignes of Gods wrath, wee are to eſteem no otherwiſe of the other ſorts of afflictions. When Satan therefore ſhall ſuggeſt unto thee what the Jewes ſaid once to Chriſt; if thou be the Sonne of God come down from the croſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.40. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him clean contrary, becauſe I am the child of God I will mount the croſſe, and through much tribulation enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, Acts 14.22. Moreover, ſince the afflictions of Gods children carry with them
<pb facs="tcp:120697:101"/> ſuch good things, and are ſignes of Gods fatherly love, they are cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſely, as they are commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, evills, but contrarily, deſerve to be ſtiled good things. To this purpole, the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, It is good for mee that I have been afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. and <hi>Jeremy,</hi> it is good for a man that he beare his yoak in his youth, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.27. Certainly hee that ſaith it is good to be afflicted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares likewiſe that afflictions are good and profitable, which muſt not be underſtood, as though they were good in their owne nature; for if thou conſidereſt all calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in their firſt Originall, they are the brood and off-ſpring of death, whereunto all men were adjudged by God's ſentence; but now they became good things in regard of the metamorphoſis, or tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their nature, when inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to Gods children, which are
<pb facs="tcp:120697:101"/> no otherwiſe then the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> made a defenced City, and an iron pillar, and brazen wals. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.18 againſt which the darts loſe their heads, and are not able to doe any hurt. That they doe change their nature, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intimateth, when hee ſaith, wee know that all things work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for good to them that love God, who are called according to his purpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 28. Of this change the croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt is the cauſe through whom God is our father. This is the tree that takes away the bitterneſſe of the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> whereinto we fall in the wilderneſſe of this world. This is that brazen Serpent, whereupon if wee look, afflictions invading us, and as it were a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent biting our heeles, our heart ſhall live, and her head ſhall be brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. He that was preſent with the three children in the midſt of the
<pb facs="tcp:120697:102"/> fiery furnace, will be preſent with us alſo, when we ſuffer-perſecution for his name ſake. The tree of the croſſe beareth excellent fruit, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of righteouſneſſe, whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: Now no chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous; nevertheleſſe, it yieldeth the peace of righteouſneſſe unto them which are exerciſed thereby, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11. ſo that to ſtile the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods children then, when their genuine nature is explicated, evils, infelicities, calamities, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, then to imitate the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of a certain undiſcreet A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary, that leaves the inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Arſenick upon his boxe, when as there is nothing elſe in it, but <hi>Rubarb</hi> or <hi>Manna;</hi> yea, it is an adulterous falſe marke, proper unto thoſe with whom Chriſt hath no communion, and unto whom puniſhments are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:102"/> but are taſtes and harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of thoſe everlaſting torments, which abide them after this life. Hence it is manifeſt, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Gods children is to bee preferred to the ſtate of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of this world: wee have declared in the beginning of this Chapter, that all afflictions are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly common, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their outward forme; ſo that there is not any adverſity, which may not as equally befall an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſinner as a godly man. The difference then conſiſteth herein, that the wicked perſevering in their ſinnes, can have no true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, becauſe they can gather no good thing out of their calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whereas the caſe is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with the afflictions of Gods children; for they procure them ineſtimable good things, and by the vertue of the croſſe of Chriſt doe become a new kind of goodneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:103"/> whereupon they find therein true, firme conſolation; ſo that certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the apprehenſion and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of afflictions, were there no other cauſe for a ſinner to returne unto God, go on in the way of ſalvation, and live in the feare of God, ſhould ſufficiently move him to be at reſt in the day of adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Laſtly, if there be ſuch good and excellent things in afflictions: If their ends bee ſo glorious and happy, why art thou therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſoule dejected and ſorrowfull in affliction, which doth now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe thee? Thou wilt ſay, becauſe it is grievous to fleſh and blood; that is true, but the caſe is of like nature in a Medicine, the taſte whereof doth not argue it to be wholſome, but its vertue and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration otherwiſe, thou mayeſt take Poyſon inſtead of Medecine, and embrace death for life: that thou mayeſt not injure and deceive thy
<pb facs="tcp:120697:103"/> ſelfe in the conſideration of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſet before thy view their fruit and end, which is very excellent, and of greater value than one is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conceive: This is it which thou ſhouldeſt think upon in thy preſent affliction. Now, ſince thy containe and procure thee ſuch good things as wee have demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, it behoves thee to bee of a joyfull mind, which St. <hi>James</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of thee; My brethren, count it all joy, when yee fall into divers temptations, <hi>Ja.</hi> 1.2. and eſpecially when thou ſuffereſt for the teſtimony of Gods truth, and conſtant profeſſion of the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Religion: rejoyce and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad, for great is your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12. but rejoyce, inaſmuch as ye are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſts ſufferings, that when his glory ſhall be revealed, yee may be glad alſo with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding joy: if ye be reproached for
<pb facs="tcp:120697:104"/> the name of Chriſt, happy are yee, for the ſpirit of glory and God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth upon you; on their part he is evill ſpoken of, but on your part he is glorified, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13,14. ſhew thy ſelfe to be a Diſciple of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who being for the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt beaten with rods, went away rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſhame for his name, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.13,14. and by Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> teſtimony, did glory in tribulations, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. Imitate the Saints among the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> who did take joyfully the ſpoiling of their goods, knowing in themſelves they had in heaven a better and more enduring ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. Neither doth it only become thee in afflictions to be joyfull, but thankfull unto God, who by this means offers thee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things, and acts the part of a Phyſician or Benefactor. Say therefore with <hi>Job,</hi> who had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
<pb facs="tcp:120697:104"/> learned this leſſon, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gave God thanks in the midſt of his afflictions, when thou art deprived of ſome earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity; The Lord gave, the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord, <hi>Job</hi> 1.21. To the end thou mayeſt be joyfull and thankfull unto thy heavenly father, conſider forthwith thoſe moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and unſpeakable good things that are in afflictions, and thereby redound unto thee; view their conſummation and glorious end, and ſay to thy ſelfe, O what gracious benefits, through afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I have obtained, which God ſends upon mee, by means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ones outward man periſheth, yet the inward is renew'd day by day, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. Say therefore for example, God deprives me of my child, thereby to make me tread more conſtantly the path of Gods children; hee hath taken away my
<pb facs="tcp:120697:105"/> father or mother, that inſtead of him he may be my father for ever, and be more carefull of mee than awoman can be of the fruit of her wombe; hee is willing I ſhould have experience of the perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my friends, that I may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his eternall love. It is his pleaſure I ſhould be deprived of authorities, dignities, and honors, that I may obtaine the honour to Lord it over all the creatures. I am driven to poverty, that I may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe that heavenly inheritance; I am detained in priſon, that I may obtaine that freedome that the ſon of God hath purchaſed for me; I am baniſhed, that I come to my heavenly countrey; I am defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and maimed in body, that I may grow to a perfect man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtature of Chriſt, and that this corruptible body may be cloathed with incorruption; I die now, to live eternally. And what
<pb facs="tcp:120697:105"/> are all the afflictions that thou ſuffereſt or couldſt endure, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou conſidereſt their quality or duration compared with thoſe ineſtimable good things which they carry with them. Conſider and meditate diligently thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſoule upon theſe things, being in affliction, which now affects thee with ſorrow; in ſo doing thy water ſhall be turned into nuptiall wine, thy ſorrow into mirth and joy; ſo thou ſhalt taſte how ſweet the Lord is, though hee ſeemes to thee at the firſt bluſh or appearance rigid, yet thou ſhalt diſcerne the rod of our heavenly <hi>Jonathan,</hi> who wrought ſo great ſalvation in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> to bee dipped at the end ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in an hony combe, which will enlighten our eyes, refreſh our hearts, teach our hands to warre, and make us more than Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; ſo that thou ſhalt find that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, not without cauſe,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:106"/> Rejoyce evermore, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.16. foraſmuch as not only the time of proſperity, but of adverſity, yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth matter of rejoycing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. The ſeventh and laſt ground or reaſon is drawne from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the faithfull man in this world, which conſiſteth herein, that hee is a traveller journeying into his countrey.</head>
               <p>IT is manifeſt by the third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon above-mentioned, that even as ſinne expelled thee out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and baniſhed thee from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, thy countrey, and firſt place of abode, ſo thou art ſolely by Gods grace called back from baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and invited to returne to thy
<pb facs="tcp:120697:106"/> Countrey. Hence it followeth, that during this life thou art in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall pilgrimage, whoſe limit or end is heaven, and eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. This world then is not thy dwelling place, and countrey, but a place of pilgrimage and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that thou mayeſt ſay with <hi>David,</hi> I am a ſtranger with thee, and a ſojourner as all my fathers were, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.12. And againe, I am a ſtranger in the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.19. why art thou then ſo ſorely troubled, and of a dejected mind, whenſoever thou art ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with adverſity? it grieves thee that all things fall not out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy mind: but art thou ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant thou art a travelling, ſo that it cannot be, that all things ſhould happen as thy heart could wiſh? for either thou muſt endure the diſcommodities of the way, or not enter into it, and conſequently ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to thy countrey. One of
<pb facs="tcp:120697:107"/> theſe conditions thou muſt chuſe, there is not a third; I ſay againe, thou muſt endure them, or obſtain wholly from travelling. If thou beeſt a traveller, as verily thou art, be of a couragious ſpirit in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for that which thou now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureſt ſhall not be perpetuall, nor ſhall laſt longer than thy journey: What traveller is there which will not endure the diſcommodities of his way, and aſſwage them with theſe or the like meditations, that upon the accompliſhment of his journey, they ſhall ceaſe, and hee be freed of them, as ſoone as hee comes home. Conſider further, that howſoever thy journey be grievous, it is but ſhort. If the dayes of thy pilgrimage will be as many as the dayes of <hi>Iacob's</hi> the Patriarch, to wit, a 130 years; yet nevertheleſſe thou mayeſt ſay with him, The dayes of the years of my pilgrimage are few and evill,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:107"/> and have not attained unto the dayes of the yeares of the life of my fathers in the dayes of their pilgrimage, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9. And when thou haſt finiſhed thy courſe, which will ſhortly come to paſſe; all afflictions, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all ſorrow ſhall ceaſe, thou hunger no more, neither ſhall the Sun light on thee, nor any heat, for the Lambe which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed thee, and ſhall lead thee unto living foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aines of waters, and God ſhall wipe away all teares from thine eyes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.16,17. Since thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt a traveller in this world, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat thy countrey is not here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow, there is no place therefore in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his world; whence if thou beeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riven, thou mayeſt ſay thou art in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aniſhment. Neither doe thy ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hes by the ſame reaſon conſiſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome earthly glebe in houſes, fields, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſome other poſſeſſion how ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:120697:108"/> or ample ſoever it be; yea, if a Kingdome or Kingdomes happen unto thee. Neither doth thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour likewiſe conſiſt in the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and preferments of this world, nor in that ſmoak wherewith emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty brains doe ſo much feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Nor doe thy delights con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the brutiſh pleaſures of the fleſh, nor is thy life incloſed within that ſpace thou liveſt in this world: for as heaven is thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſo are thy riches of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, the inheritance of the Saints prepared for thee. Thy honour and dignity conſiſteth herein, that thou art the child of God, and haſt ſoveraignty over all the creatures; Thy delights and pleaſures are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God; thy joy is in his preſence, where is fulneſſe of joy, and at his right hand there is pleaſure for ever more, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.12. Thy life is that of eternity, into which upon the accompliſhment
<pb facs="tcp:120697:108"/> of thy pilgrimage thou entreſt, ſo that when thou art dead thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneſt really to live. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, goods, and commodities of this world, what are they but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which befall thee in thy pilgrimage? no otherwiſe than ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, but with this difference; that whereas thoſe moſtly bring the traveller from the right way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by-wayes, theſe above all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination cauſe the children of God with more alacrity to accompliſh their journey. It followeth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that thy miſeries conſiſt not in the want or loſſe of the goods of this world, then indeed thou ſhouldeſt bee miſerable, if thou ſhouldeſt not attaine to thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, nor obtaine that happineſſe whereunto thou bendeſt thy courſe. Seeing thy life and countrey is in heaven, and art moſt aſſured of the goods, honours, and delights of the ſame, thou canſt in no wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:120697:109"/> think thy ſelfe to bee unhappy, if thou haſt righteous judgement. Let not the loſſe or want of that that is not thine afflict thee, and turn not the intereſt into the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, the way into thy journeyes end, thy Inne into thy home and countrey. Reſt not upon that good which is not thine own, place not thy happineſſe therein, neglecting the true felicity: It is a fools trick, to weep at the loſſe of his cap, and to laugh when hee ſees his owne houſe ſet on fire. Moreover, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thou art a traveller, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing towards heaven, bee of a couragious ſpirit in all thy affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, when they would diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and poſſeſſe thee with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, oppoſing unto them the ſcope of thy journey, and high calling. Rejoyce in a moſt aſſured hope of obtaining thy heavenly countrey, the kingdome of glory, life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, goods, honour, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable
<pb facs="tcp:120697:109"/> pleaſures. Know this, there is nothing worthy thy perſon but heaven, and that all the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this world is unworthy thy thoughts and deſires; the earth too baſe, and all things therein too vile and abject to be given thee, for thou art Gods child, and in a way to poſſeſſe a Kingdome. Away then with every abject thought, which affecteth the vulgar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ſort; away with all heavineſſe and ſorrow, let thy face import, and thy eyes and outward geſtures teſtifie, that thou beareſt in thy boſome ſuch a high generous ſpirit, as beſeems the majeſty of him, who after a ſhort time ended is to exerciſe dominion over all the creatures. Furthermore, ſince thou art a traveller, as often as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall ſtrive to invade thee, ſay within thy ſelfe, ſhall I vexe and macerate my ſelfe, as if I had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſineſſe, God forbid, God
<pb facs="tcp:120697:110"/> forbid. I am a traveller, and I have other buſineſſes than ſtand ſtil in the way, play the idle-bee, and indulge my ſelfe to weep and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my ſelfe; for I have a long way to go with <hi>Eliah,</hi> yea, longer than I am able of my ſelfe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme: I muſt ſeriouſly conſider of this way, how I may make a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous end of it, and overcome the diſcommodities obvious there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. To this end all neceſſary means art to be uſed, faith, hope, patience, conſtancy, prayers, and all good workes, which God before ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that we ſhould walk in them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. Moreover, very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deadly dangers offer themſelves to my view, and moſt potent ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to wit, the world, and that horrible mighty infernall Goliah, and my own fleſh eſpecially, which is my moſt dangerous enemy. Theſe enemies lie in wait for mee continually, aſſaulting mee one
<pb facs="tcp:120697:110"/> while on the right hand, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while on the left: while they ſet upon mee, and make at mee, ſhall I be ſo unhappy and fooliſh, as to ſuffer them to aſſault mee uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled? ſhall I hide my hands in my boſome? ſhall I buſie my ſelfe in things of no moment or worth? No, at no hand, I may not prove a daſtard, but moſt valiantly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, I am undone elſe, and muſt periſh upon the way, and my carkaſſe ſhall be throwne into the infernall valley; wherein are more grievous diſcommodities, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whereof all evils which are commonly ſo called, dangers, and moleſtations, are but trifles and toyes; ſo here thou ſhouldeſt have cauſe to be ſorrowful, to grieve and macerate thy ſelfe: ſix thy mind upon this, inſtead of grieving ſo much for theſe worldly things. Think, ſaith a certain father, upon the miſery of thy pilgrimage, call
<pb facs="tcp:120697:111"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120697:111"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:120697:112"/> to mind thy yeares paſt in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of thy ſoule, think upon the dangers of humane life, and thy owne frailty; and if thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevereſt in the conſideration hereof, I tell thee thou wilt ſcarce be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of outward moleſtations, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven whilſt thy heart is poſſeſſed of inward ſorrow. Think diligently upon all theſe things, thou faithfull ſoule, ſo thou ſhalt eaſily diſcharge thy ſelfe of all manner of ſorrow, and ſhalt be a wiſe, happy travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Hee that otherwiſe doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what the children of this world are wont to doe, whereof each is like a fooliſh traveller, who being in exile, and permitted by his Princes grace to come home, ſets forth, being deſirous to come to his countrey, but he is entangled in difficulties, and thouſand foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; for as he applies himſelfe to his journey, hee makes a grievous complaint, that he hath not provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:120697:113"/> enough, being not contented to have ſo much as will ſuffice him during his journey, but what will laſt a long time after, though hee hath all manner of dainties in his owne countrey; hee is angry he is not cloathed with a winter ſuit, though hee travelleth in the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time; and it grieves him, that he hath not more toyes than hee is able to carry about him. When he is ſatisfied herein, and ſo driven to his journey, then perhaps, if one of his fellow exiles takes not his leave of him in courteous and very gracious words, he takes time to expoſtulate with him, neither will he go forward, till the Judge put a period to this brangle; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, hee again applies himſelf to his journey; but behold, a Hare croſſing his way, being thereupon frighted, as by an ill augury, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes to the place of his baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where being taught by a
<pb facs="tcp:120697:114"/> certain friend of his, that the Hares croſſing his way was but a caſuall thing, portending no evill. And ſo againe hee addreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his journey, wherein hee ſpends his time and labour marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly in vaine, and diſquiets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with many buſineſſes; for as hee paſſeth through the wood, hee numbers the trees very carefully, and rubs the moſſe there-from, to ſee whether that which <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaks of, according to the vulgar opinion, be true; that there be ſo many branches upon a tree as there be roots; and look with how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny boughes it is beautified and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned, with ſo many roots it is faſtned in the earth. And after hee hath for a long time beſtowed his labour in vaine upon this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, he applies himſelfe to his journey againe; and by chance there is a greater noiſe of the leaves than wonted, thereupon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb facs="tcp:120697:112"/> a knot of theeves to bee at hand, hee takes him his heeles and runnes away, leaving all his things behind him; and for this turne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth his journey, and returnes to the place whence he came at firſt: and howſoever he be diſpoſſeſſed of that feare, yet hee ceaſeth not to be childiſh; for ſeeing a ſtone in the midſt of the way, which he might paſſe by, he turnes not aſide, but endeavours to break it into ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and thereupon fals headlong to the ground. Being in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture hee makes a piteous moane, and yet ſtriveth not to get up; and if perchance one paſſe by, moved with compaſſion, endeavours to lift him up, hee is froward, teſty, and complaines of him, who rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth a helping hand, yea, reviles him with reproaches. And if it happens he be wet with raine, hee ſteeres his courſe to a place diſtant thence ten dayes journey, onely
<pb facs="tcp:120697:113"/> upon this deſigne, to drie his cloathes. And when hee comes to the Inne, if all the rooms, beſides that which is alotted him, bee not handſome, richly adorned, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with hangings; or if the beds be not ſoft enough, and he be not entertained with an over-deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate feaſt, being unmindfull of his journey, hee ſtayes there to raile with his hoaſt, menacing to bring him before the Judge: But being in ſome ſort reconciled with him, he beſtowes much coſt and paines in repairing that Inne, that he may the next time that hee comes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which will be at latter Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, be better entertained: but if the ſtructure and building corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponds not with his mind, with a broken and deſpairing ſpirit, hee goes even the ſame way backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and returnes to the place whence he came at firſt. <hi>In fine,</hi> hee diſquiets himſelf in a thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:120697:114"/> turmoiles and troubles, and all to no purpoſe, whereof hee might have been diſpoſſeſſed, had hee not applied his mind unto ſuch things as were obvious in his way, and been not unmindfull of his duty. Countrey, and condition. The condition of the child of this world is of the ſame ſtraine; hee forgets his journey, and ſpirituall courſe, which hee is bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme; hee interrupts and breaks off in the midſt of his pilgrimage, beginning it againe and againe; ſo that in the latter end of his life, he is a ſtrange gueſt to true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as hee was at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The ſinner being an hundred yeares old ſhall bee accuſed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.20. he is ſo fooliſh, that though he hath now and then purpoſed with himſelfe to renounce the world, yet never brings his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to perfection, but beginning in the ſpirit, he endeth in the fleſh,
<pb facs="tcp:120697:115" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3. The reaſon whereof is, becauſe he inſteed of meditating upon his heavenly countrey, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves himſelfe in the things of this world; whereupon his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo fixt, that nothing beſides moſt grievous miſeries can recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile him unto God, and bring him into the right way to his heavenly Countrey. Thou devout ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have thy ſelf otherwiſe, and be like a wiſe traveller; go from ſtrength to ſtrength, till thou appeare before God in <hi>Sion, Pſal.</hi> 84.8. ſo that thou mayeſt have this teſtimony and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation with the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> in thy ſelfe, and mayeſt ſay; But this one thing I doe, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before, I preſſe toward the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen Phil.</hi> 3.13,14.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:120697:115"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
